<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A paraphrase with notes upon the sixth chapter of St. John with a discourse on humanity and charity / by W. Claget.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08083977</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08083977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1226:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A paraphrase with notes upon the sixth chapter of St. John with a discourse on humanity and charity / by W. Claget.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>xxxii, 124 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Robinson and T. Newborough,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A discourse of humanity and charity." p. [71]-98 has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>"A letter concerning Protestants charity to Papists" p. 99-124.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John VI --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Charity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:1"/>
                  <p>A PARAPHRASE WITH NOTES Upon the Sixth Chapter of St. <hi>JOHN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With a Diſcourſe on <hi>Humanity and Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>W. CLAGET,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="imprimatur">
                     <body>
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Jo. Battely <hi>RR<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> Patri ac D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no</hi>
                              </hi> Wilhelmo <hi>Archiepiſc. Cantuar. à Sacris Domesticis.</hi>
                           </signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>Ex Edibus Lambeth,</hi> 
                              <date>Maii 31. 1686.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lion,</hi> and <hi>T. Newborough</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1693.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:2"/>
                  <pb n="i" facs="tcp:40809:2"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>'TIS not for nothing that we are deſired to read the Sixth Chapter of St. <hi>John</hi> every day. I have engaged my Thoughts with what attention I can, upon thoſe Paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>51</hi> and <hi>61</hi> Verſes; and the more I conſider them, the more favourably they ſeem to me to look upon that Opinion, that the <hi>very Fleſh</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is eaten in the Sacrament. I know not what to ſay to this, that though the <hi>Jews</hi> underſtood <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Words, of eating his very Fleſh, and he ſaw plainly enough that they did ſo, yet he went on in the ſame ſtrain of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, <hi>Verily verily I ſay unto you, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you.</hi> I know you told me, that theſe Paſſages are not to be interpreted of the Sacrament; and that there is no mention in them of any outward and viſible Signs; which are neceſſary to a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I have heard that the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:40809:3"/> thought theſe words to be ſpoken of the Sacrament. And beſides, though there be no mention of a Sacrament, yet if <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Words enforce this, that the natural Subſtance of his Fleſh muſt be properly eaten by us, it will follow that it muſt be thus eaten in the Sacrament of his Body and Blood, unleſs we could tell how or where elſe it is to be done. I would be glad to ſee ſuch a Paraphraſe upon this Chapter, as you ſpeak of, which would help to make all appear plain. And it were well if others might ſee it too, and thereby ſee this at leaſt, that you are ſo well ſatisfy'd with your own Reaſons, that you are not afraid to let thoſe judge of them that are otherwiſe perſwaded.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I am, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:40809:3"/>
                  <head>The <hi>PREFACE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YOU are deſired to read the 6th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel every day; and this I doubt not, for the ſake of that part of it between <hi>V.</hi> 51, and <hi>V.</hi> 61; which ſeems to require <hi>eating the Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking the Blood of Chriſt</hi> in the proper ſenſe. And here I make no queſtion your Thoughts were cloſely engaged. But perhaps you have not applied that attention to the reſt of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which you gave to that part where the difficulty lies, and then no wonder that the difficulty ſtill remains. For I beg leave to put you in mind, once more, that the true Senſe of thoſe difficult Paſſages, as you count them, is to be gained by obſerving their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with all the reſt. And therefore to that Requeſt, that you would often read the 6th Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> which I acknowledge to be a reaſonable Requeſt, I muſt add ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as reaſonable as that, which is, that you would not only often <hi>read,</hi> but likewiſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>conſider the whole Chapter,</hi> and mind our Saviour's Deſign in it: That you would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerve what ſort of People he had to do with, and what was the occaſion of this Converſation between him and them: What
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:40809:4"/> was the Fundamental Cauſe of their Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt him; and with what Arguments and Applications he laboured to remove thoſe Prejudices.</p>
                  <p>For you will then find, that they were Men whoſe <hi>Belly was their God,</hi> and <hi>who mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed earthly things;</hi> that they followed <hi>Chriſt</hi> for the <hi>Loaves;</hi> that he diſappointed their Hopes; that they were angry at it, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered their Opinion of him upon it; that their earthly-mindedneſs was the Reaſon why they now liked him not, but ſet themſelves to cavil at all his Sayings; that to take them off from the Cares and Pleaſures of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life, he laid before them better and greater Things, the Means and Hopes of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life: Finally, that he calls the Means and Cauſes of bettering our Minds, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to everlaſting Life, <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink;</hi> and our believing and obeying his Doctrine, <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking.</hi> And then, if I am not deceived, you will eaſily acknowledge, that in particular, he calls the Belief of his Death and Paſſion for the Sins of the World, and the ſaving Fruits of that Faith, <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood:</hi> And that there is no more reaſon to imagine that his Fleſh ſhould be eaten, and his Blood drank, in the proper and corporeal ſenſe, than that he ſhould make himſelf <hi>Bread</hi> to be eaten by us, as we uſe to eat Bread: But that there is good reaſon to underſtand throughout, by that <hi>eating</hi> and
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:40809:4"/> 
                     <hi>drinking</hi> which he required, ſpiritual Actions only, which the whole ſtrain of his Diſcourſe ſhews, that he oppoſed to that corporeal feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which they were ſo inordinately ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for.</p>
                  <p>I muſt for the ſame Reaſon deſire you to mind thoſe plain Intimations ſcattered here and there in our Lord's Diſcourſe; by which it is evident, what he meant by <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>V.</hi> 29. <hi>This is the</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Work of God, that ye BELIEVE on him whom he hath ſent;</hi> which is an Interpretation of <hi>V.</hi> 27.<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Labour not for the meat that periſheth, but,</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>V.</hi> 35. <hi>He that BELIEVETH on me, ſhall never thirſt.</hi> And again, <hi>V.</hi> 47. <hi>He that BELIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VETH on me, hath everlaſting Life.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>V.</hi> 36. and <hi>V.</hi> 40. This, I ſay, is fit to be minded. For when not only the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion he had to uſe theſe Terms of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> (which was their following him for their Bellies) ſhews theſe Terms to be alluſive; but (as if that were not enough) he likewiſe added, now and then, the plain and proper meaning of thoſe Alluſions; it muſt, I think, be a wilful Miſtake in him that attends to this, to interpret thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as if they were not alluſive.</p>
                  <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:40809:5"/>
                  <p>Nor is this all; for you may pleaſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider alſo, that when our Saviour found ſome of his Diſciples to underſtand him as the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Jews</hi> did, he thought fit, for more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſatisfaction, to explain his meaning once for all, <hi>V.</hi> 62, 63. as you will find by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Paraphraſe and Notes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for our Saviour's repeating thoſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions at which the <hi>Jews</hi> had already ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken offence; you may conſider, that <hi>V.</hi> 51. he added that Expreſſion of <hi>drinking his Blood,</hi> to that of <hi>eating his Fleſh;</hi> which was a more plain Intimation of that violent Death which he was to ſuffer for us, than that former Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of <hi>giving his Fleſh for the Life of the World.</hi> And ſo, tho' he kept ſtill to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, yet he repreſented what kind of Death he was to ſuffer, more fully than he had done before. But perhaps you are at a loſs why he continued to ſpeak alluſively at all, when he found that he was ſo groſly miſtunderſtood. And then I anſwer, as I have done in the Notes upon that place, that I am not obliged to ſay preciſely what our Saviour's reaſon was for that. But, beſides what you will find there, it may be ſaid, that ſometimes it well becomes a Man of Wiſdom and Authority, when he finds his Words perverted by cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People, to repeat them again, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſpeak his own Aſſurance, that they did not drop unadviſedly from him, and that 'tis not his own but his Hearers Fault, that he is
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:40809:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> miſunderſtood. And this is the more reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be ſaid in the preſent caſe, if the <hi>Jews wilfully perverted</hi> our Saviour's Words to that abſurd ſenſe of eating his Fleſh with their Teeth, as 'tis probably they did; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Expreſſions were plainly alluſive, and becauſe alſo the Alluſion was now and then explain'd, as I ſhew'd before. What inconvenience is it therefore to ſuppoſe that our Lord perceiving that his Divine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes and Exhortations had but hardened them in a Spirit of Contradiction, did not think himſelf bound to uſe preſently the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt plainneſs of Words for the ſake of Men, to whom he had ſpoken plainly enough al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, if any good were to be done upon them. But for further ſatisfaction in this matter, I refer you once more to the <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe</hi> and <hi>Notes,</hi> which are already finiſhed, and where ſome little Light is given to thoſe Paſſages which may ſeem obſcure; enough, I hope, to lead you out of all danger of ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>V.</hi> 51, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to enforce that the Subſtance of his Fleſh muſt be eaten by us, either <hi>in</hi> or <hi>out</hi> of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>It ſeems I told you, that theſe Paſſages were not to be underſtood of the Sacrament; I ſhould have added, that becauſe they ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy thoſe things which are ſignify'd in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, that they may be very aptly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Sacrament, eſpecially in Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:40809:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to Devotion; nay, and that there are ſome caſes in which a Man may argue from the one to the other, and ſome Queſtions to which both the one and the other give equal Light: which may very well be, and yet it will by no means follow, that theſe words are primarily to be underſtood of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> And this Opinion I cannot deliver up, meerly becauſe you have heard that the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways held the contrary. No Man, I believe, has a greater regard to the conſtant and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Tradition of the Church than my ſelf. But then I do not think my ſelf bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Church has always held this or that, becauſe this and that Man tells me ſo. For if a Man can ſpeak, and has a Cauſe to ſerve, 'tis as eaſie to ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Church,</hi> as to ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Scripture.</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber indeed, that our Country-man <hi>Nicholas Sanders</hi> tells us, That<note n="(c)" place="margin">Nic. Sanderus de Euchar. p. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>to deny theſe words to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the Euchariſt, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Inſtruction and Authority of all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity.</hi> And <hi>Maldonate</hi> ſays, <hi>That</hi>
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">Maldon. in Joan. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>all the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers acknowledge it.</hi> And others ſay the ſame thing; and it ſeems you have heard it. Now this is but a cuſtom of ſpeaking, which ſome Men have gotten: For I am well aſſured, that all the Fathers were not of their mind.</p>
                  <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:40809:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi>
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Paedag.</hi> lib. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. p. 105. Pariſ.</note> ſuppoſes theſe Expreſſions, to <hi>eat the Fleſh of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>to drink his Blood,</hi> to be as figurative as that of St. <hi>Paul, to feed with Milk;</hi> and tells us, upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the word is <hi>variouſly allegorized,</hi> being called <hi>Meat, and Fleſh, and Nouriſhment, and Bread, and Blood, and Milk;</hi> and that <hi>our Lord is all theſe things for our enjoyment who believe in him.</hi> Now I am perſwaded you will not ſay that this Father interpreted the Words under Debate of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian,</hi> to ſhew that theſe Words, <hi>the Fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> do not make againſt the <hi>Reſurrection of the Fleſh,</hi> ſaith,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Sic etſi carnem ait nihil prodeſſe, ex materia dicti dirigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt ſenſus. Nam quia durum &amp; intolerabilem exiſtimaverunt ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ejus, quaſi vere Carnem ſuam illis eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam determinaſſet, ut in Spiritum diſponeret ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſalutis, praemiſit, Spiritus eſt qui vivificat, atque ita ſubjunxit, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro nihil prodeſt, ad vivificandum ſcilicet, Exequitur etiam quid ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit intelligi ſpiritum. Verba quae locutus ſum vobis Spiritus ſunt, Vita ſunt. Sicut &amp; ſupra, qui audit Sermones meos &amp; credit in eum qui, &amp;c. Ita<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Sermonem conſtituens vivificatorem, quia Spiritus &amp; Vita Sermo, eundem etiam Carnem ſuam dixit, quia &amp; ſermo Caro erat Pactus, proinde in cauſam Vitae Appetendus &amp; devorandus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditu, &amp; ruminandus intellectu, &amp; Fide digerendus. Nam &amp; paulo ante Carnem ſuam panem quo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Coeleſtem pronunciaret; urgens uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quequa<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> per Allegoriam, &amp;c. <hi>Tertul. de Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r. Carnis,</hi> c. 36, 37.</note> That <hi>we are to be directed to the ſence of what is ſaid by the ſubject-matter of it. For becauſe they thought his ſaying hard and intollerable, as if he intended his Fleſh ſhould be truly eaten
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:40809:7"/> by them; he to ſhew that the Cauſe of Life and Salvation was ſpiritual, premiſed this,</hi> That the Spirit quickneth; <hi>and then added,</hi> The Fleſh profiteth nothing, <hi>that is, in reſpect of quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And then he ſhews what he means by the Spirit.</hi> The words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life. <hi>As he had ſaid alſo before,</hi> He that heareth my words, and believeth in him that ſent me, hath Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, and ſhall not come into Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but hath paſſed from Death to Life. <hi>Therefore making his Word to be the quickning Principle; ſince his Word is Spirit and Life, he called his Word alſo his own Fleſh; for the Word was alſo made Fleſh: and therefore in order to Life, it is to be hungred after, and devoured by HEARING, and to be chewed again by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDERSTANDING, and to be digeſted by FAITH.</hi> And afterwards he affirms, that our Lord <hi>all along urged</hi> his Intent by an <hi>Allegory.</hi> So that <hi>Tertullian</hi> was ſo far from thinking theſe Paſſages to refer to the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> that I am in ſome doubt whether he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood them with any ſpecial reference to the Death of <hi>Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Origen</hi> alſo interprets <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in like manner: For, ſays he,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Carnibus enim &amp; ſanguine Verbi ſui, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam mundo cibo at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> potu reficit omne homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num genus. <hi>Orig. in Levit. Hom.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>By the Fleſh and the Blood of his WORD, as with pure Meat and Drink he refreſheth all Mankind.</hi>
                     <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:40809:7"/> And<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> in Mat. Tract. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> elſewhere he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> likewiſe ſeems to me to be of the ſame Opinion, who ſpeaking of the literal ſence in which the Jews underſtood our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, hath theſe words,<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. Athan. in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud Evangelii. <hi>Quincun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dixerit,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>For how could his Body ſuffice for ſo many to eat of, that it ſhould become nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the whole World? It is,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he mentioned the Son of Man's aſcending into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that he might draw them off from the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Notion.</hi> Which Teſtimony, as it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſhewed his Judgment to be, that our Saviour did not require the proper eating of his <hi>Natural</hi> Body; ſo it contains a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Argument, that he did not underſtand thoſe Words of eating his <hi>Sacramental</hi> Body. For if he had ſo underſtood them, it had been very accountable that the Body of <hi>Chriſt, i. e.</hi> his Sacramental Body, was ſufficient for the nouriſhment of the whole World. And by removing all <hi>Corporeal Notions</hi> of eating and drinking, he ſeem'd to eſtabliſh only a <hi>Spiritual Notion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But St. <hi>Hierom</hi> is plain and full to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, beyond all contradiction, as I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded.
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:40809:8"/> For thus he ſpeaks,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Quando dicit qui non comederit Carnem meam &amp; biberit San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem meum, licet &amp; in Myſterio poſſet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligi, tamen verius Corpus Chriſti &amp; San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis ejus Sermo Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum eſt, Doctrina Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina eſt.—Si quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do audimus Sermonem Dei; Sermo Dei, &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Chriſti, &amp; Sanguis ejus in auribus noſtris funditur, &amp; nos aliud cogitamus in quantum periculum incurrimus? — Sic &amp; in Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Chriſti, qui eſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo Doctrinae, hoc eſt Scripturarum Sancta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Interpretatio, ſicut volumus ita &amp; cibum accipimus. <hi>Hieron. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Pſal.</hi> 147.</note> 
                     <hi>When</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſaith,</hi> He that eateth not my Fleſh, and drinketh not my Blood, <hi>although it may be underſtood in a Myſtery, (i. e.</hi> as I think, of the <hi>Euchariſt) yet the truer ſence is, that the Body of Chriſt, and his Blood, is the Word of the Scriptures, is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Doctrine.</hi> — And therefore he continues not long after in this manner; <hi>If when we hear the Word of God; the Word of God, and the Fleſh of Chriſt, and his Blood, is poured into our Ears, and we think of ſomething elſe, into how great a danger do we run?</hi> Afterwards comparing it to <hi>Manna,</hi> which was ſaid to give that Taſte to every Man which he liked beſt. <hi>So,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the Fleſh of Chriſt; which is the Word of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that is, the Interpretation of the Holy Scriptures; as we would have it, ſo we receive Food. If thou art holy,</hi> here <hi>thou findeſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> St. <hi>Hierom</hi> could not have been more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, if he had been to maintain this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation againſt an Adverſary.</p>
                  <p>Nor does the Paraphraſe of <hi>Euſebius</hi> come much behind St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s Interpretation. For he makes our Saviour's Explication, <hi>V.</hi> 63. to
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:40809:8"/> run as if he had ſaid,<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Euſeb. Caeſarienſis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Marcel. de Eccleſ. Theol. lib. 3. c. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Do not think that I ſpeak of that Fleſh which I carry about me, as if you ought to eat that, or that I command you to drink my ſenſible and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Blood. You well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the words which I ſpeak to you, are Spirit and Life. So that,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> goes on, <hi>his Words and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are Fleſh and Blood, of which whoever conſtantly partakes, he being nouriſhed with Heavenly Bread, as it were, ſhall partake of the Heavenly Life.</hi> He that ſays this, and knows what he ſays, could hardly ſuppoſe that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly intended by our Saviour in theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall trouble you with no more Inſtances of this kind, theſe being ſufficient to ſhew, that <hi>All</hi> the Ancients did not underſtand thoſe words of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> And now I will make no difficulty to grant that the other Opinion is not deſtitute of all Authority, but has the Countenance of ſome Fathers to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it. For we do not pretend to any ſuch priviledge of ſpeaking, as to ſay, we have <hi>All</hi> the Fathers, in a Caſe where we have not <hi>every One.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:40809:9"/>
                  <p>But this I muſt needs ſay, That thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who, as far as I have yet diſcovered, ſeem to ſpeak moſt expreſly in favour of the <hi>Sacramental</hi> Senſe, do not come up to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorineſs and clearneſs of thoſe who are for the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Senſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">Cypr. de Orat. Dom.</note>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>daily Bread</hi> which we pray for, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of common Food, but of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies thoſe Words to it; <hi>If any man eateth of this Bread, he ſhall live for ever.</hi> And, ſays he, <hi>as 'tis manifeſt, that</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Qui corpus ejus at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingunt.</note> 
                     <hi>they who belong to his Body,</hi> [or Family] <hi>and having a right thereunto, communicate in the Euchariſt, do live; ſo it is to be feared, and we are to pray, leſt any of us being excommunicated and ſeparated from the Body of Chriſt, ſhould be far removed from Salvation, ſince himſelf uttered this threatning, Except ye eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now I deſire not to make leſs of theſe words than they imply. But yet I muſt ſay, that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſeems, in theſe and in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Words, which are to the ſame purpoſe, to interpret that <hi>Bread, which he that eateth of, ſhall live for ever;</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not only of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> but of all the Means of Grace that are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to his Members in the Communion of his Body; whereof, as he had reaſon, he
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:40809:9"/> thought the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to be the principal, to which no excommunicated Perſon had right. Not to ſay that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> might be here particularly mentioned, becauſe thoſe words, <hi>Except ye eat</hi> &amp;c. have a more clear alluſion to the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> than to any other Means. Nor am I alone in this Interpretation of St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian;</hi>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Notae in Cypr. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ.</note> For thus ſaith <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orius, The Explication of this place is taken from</hi> Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Cap. 6. de Orat. <hi>Therefore by deſiring daily Bread, we pray for a perpetual continuance in Chriſt, and to remain undivided from his Body.</hi> Thus alſo <hi>Rigaltius</hi> upon the place; <hi>The words of God the Father, which Chriſt in the Fleſh brought for our Salvation,</hi> are here to be underſtood. <hi>Therefore all that time in which Chriſt lived amongſt us in the Body, his Preaching, his Goſpel, is the Body and Fleſh of Chriſt. It is the Croſs of Chriſt, 'tis the Blood of Chriſt. With this Meat and Drink we Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are nouriſh'd to eternal Life.</hi> By which 'tis manifeſt, that <hi>Rigaltius</hi> did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in that manner, as to abate at all of his Judgment, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Obſerv. Galeat. in Cypr. Id.</note> ſpiritual ſenſe of eating and drinking, is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood throughout in the 6th of St. <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="(n)" place="margin">Baſil. Moral. Reg. 21.</note>St. <hi>Baſil</hi> is another who applies theſe Words to the Sacrament; not where he undertakes to give their proper meaning,
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:40809:10"/> but in his <hi>moral</hi> Collections, under the Head of receiving the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> which I do not ſee but he might do, and yet believe that the Spiritual Senſe of eating and drinking <hi>Chriſt</hi> was directly intended. For, as I have already told you, the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> repreſents the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and our Spiritual feeding thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and theſe words in St. <hi>John</hi> ſignifie what the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> repreſents. No wonder therefore if <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Writers, in ſpeaking of the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> produce theſe words, which have ſo near an affinity with it. And this I think they may do pertinently enough, without ſuppoſing that theſe Paſſages in St. <hi>John</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> becauſe they ſignifie ſome of the ſame things which the <hi>Eucharist</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> indeed brings forth that ſaying, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. in his Diſputations againſt the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> ſuppoſing there, as it ſhould ſeem, that it was a direct and proper Command to receive the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> under the penalty of Damnation: And I remember, that in one place he urges it for the neceſſity of <hi>Communicating Infants.</hi> This is ſo noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly known, that I ſhall not turn to the places; and though I will not be poſitive, yet I think he is not clear for this Senſe, in any other Cauſe, but that wherein he was enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt the <hi>Pelagians.</hi> But there is this very great Prejudice againſt his Authority in this matter, that elſewhere, <hi>viz.</hi> out of the
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:40809:10"/> Heat of that Controverſie, he gives clearly another ſence of theſe words, and ſpeaks of them as if they were reductive only to the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> Mark therefore what he ſays;<note n="(o)" place="margin">Hunc ita<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cibum &amp; potum ſocietatem vult intelligi corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; membrorum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum, quod eſt Sancta Eccleſia in praedeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; vocatis, &amp; juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis, &amp; glorificatis San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis, &amp; fidelibus ejus. —Hujus rei Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, id eſt, unitatis Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti, alicubi quotidie, alicubi certis intervallis dierum in Dominicâ Mensâ praeparatur, &amp; de Mensâ Dominicâ ſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quibuſdam ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, quibuſdam ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itium. Res vero ipſa cujus Sacramentum eſt, omni homini ad vitam, nulli ad exitium quicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ejus particeps fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Aug. Tract.</hi> 26. <hi>in Johan.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Therefore by this Meat and Drink, he would have us to underſtand the Society of his Body and Members, that is, the Holy Church, conſist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his predeſtinated, and called, and justified, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Saints and Faithful.</hi> And preſently after; <hi>The Sacrament of this thing, that is, of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Christ, is in ſome places every day, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places upon certain days prepared upon the Lord's Table, and received from the Lord's Table; by ſome to Life, by ſome to Destruction. But the thing it ſelf, of which it is the Sacrament, is for Life to every Man, for Destruction to no Man, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be that partakes of it.</hi> By which words it is evident, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did not here underſtand, that eating of the Fleſh, and drinking of the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to which Salvation is promiſed; of <hi>ſacramental</hi> eating, but of being incorporated into the Inviſible Church of <hi>Christ:</hi> and this, becauſe he ſays, <hi>The Sacrament of this thing may be received
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:40809:11"/> to Deſtruction;</hi> and becauſe he expreſly ſays, That <hi>this Meat and Drink is the Society of the Body of Chriſt, conſiſting of his predeſtinated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Members.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that therefore he would not have ſcrupled to interpret <hi>eating</hi> by <hi>believing;</hi> ſince 'tis Faith by which we are united to the Body of Chriſt, no reaſonable Man will queſtion. However, we have his own Word for it, who upon that Saying of our Saviour, <hi>This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent,</hi> Goes on thus,<note n="†" place="margin">Hoc eſt ergo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducare cibum, non qui perit, ſed qui perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in vitam eternam. Ut quid paras dentes &amp; ventrem? Crede &amp; manducaſti. <hi>Id. Tract.</hi> 25.</note> 
                     <hi>This therefore is to eat that Food which periſheth not, but endureth to everlasting Life. To what purpoſe doſt thou make ready thy Teeth and thy Belly? Believe, and thou haſt eaten.</hi> Afterwards he puts both together;<note n="*" place="margin">Accedat, credat, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporetur ut vivifice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Id. Tract.</hi> 26.</note> 
                     <hi>Let him come and believe, and be incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, that he may be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Words of his are the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe in that place he profeſſedly treats of the Expoſition of this Chapter. Where alſo upon that ſaying, <hi>He that eateth my Fleſh and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him,</hi> he diſcourſeth thus.
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:40809:11"/>
                     <note n="(p)" place="margin">Hoc eſt manducare eſcam illam &amp; illum bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere potum, in Chriſto manere, &amp; illum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentem in me habere. Ac per hoc, qui non manet in Chriſto, &amp; in quo Chriſtus non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, proculdubio nec manducat ſpiritualiter carnem ejus nec bibit ejus ſanguinem, licet carnaliter &amp; viſibiliter premat dentibus Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Corporis &amp; Sanguinis Chriſti, ſed magis tantae rei Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad judicium ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi manducat &amp; bibit, quia immundus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumſit ad Chriſti acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere Sacramenta, quae aliquis non digne ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, niſi qui mundus eſt, &amp;c. <hi>Tract.</hi> 26. <hi>in Joh.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>This it is to eat that Food, and drink that Drink,</hi> viz. <hi>to dwell in Chriſt, and to have Chriſt dwelling in me. And therefore he that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in Chriſt, and in whom Chriſt dwelleth not, undoubtedly doth not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eat his Fleſh, nor drink his Blood, although he doth carnally and viſibly preſs with his Teeth the Sacrament of his Body and Blood; but he rather eats and drinks the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of ſo great a thing to his Condemnation; becauſe being impure, he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to come to Chriſt's Sacraments, which none worthily receives who is not pure; of which 'tis ſaid, Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Whence it is manifeſt, that in St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>'s Judgment, <hi>to eat the Fleſh of Chriſt, and to drink his Blood,</hi> was to eat and drink it <hi>Spiritually,</hi> ſo as good and holy Men only do partake thereof, not all that do preſs the Sacrament thereof with their Teeth. And it is further obſervable, that if <hi>to eat that Food, and drink that Drink<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> be as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays, <hi>to dwell in Chriſt, and to have Chriſt dwell in us;</hi> then all holy Perſons do conſtantly e t the Fleſh, and drink the blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtill dwell in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:40809:12"/> them; but they are not always receiving the Sacrament, and therefore St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> could not underſtand theſe words properly of the <hi>Eucharist.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that theſe were not ſudden Notions of his, appears from this, that we find them elſewhere, and particularly in his Book of the <hi>City of God,</hi> towards the end; which Book he finiſhed juſt before his Death. There he hath theſe words;<note n="(q)" place="margin">Nec iſti ergo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi ſunt manducare Corpus Chriſti, quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am nec in membris computandi ſunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. Ut. enim alia ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceam, non poſſunt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul eſſe, &amp; Membra Chriſti, &amp; Membra Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retricis. Denique ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dicens, qui man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat Carnem meam, &amp; bibit Sanguinem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in me manet, &amp; ego in eo: oſtendit quid fit non Sacramento tenus, ſed reverâ Corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti manducare &amp; ejus Sanguinem bibere; hoc eſt enim in Chriſto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, ut in illo maneat &amp; Chriſtus. Sic enim hoc dicit tanquam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret. Qui non in me manet, &amp; in quo ego non maneo, non ſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat aut exiſtimet man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducare Corpus meum, aut bibere Sanguinem meum. <hi>De Civit. Dei. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> 
                     <hi>For neither are they to be ſaid to eat the Body of Chriſt, becauſe neither are they to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt his Members. For to omit other things, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be both the Members of Chriſt, and the Members of an Harlot. Laſtly, himſelf ſaying, He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me and I in him, ſheweth what it is to eat the Body of Chriſt, and drink his Blood, not by the Sacrament, but verily and indeed; for this is to dwell in Chriſt, ſo as that Chriſt dwelleth in him. For his ſpeaking this, was as if he had ſaid, He that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in me, and in whom I dwell not, ſhould not ſay or think that he eateth my Fleſh, or drinketh my Blood.</hi> Now the Perſons here
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:40809:12"/> ſpoken of were <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of vicious Lives, who yet received the Sacrament, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the Communion of the Church to the laſt. But ſince St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> denying that they <hi>ate the Body of Chriſt in Truth,</hi> even when they received the Sacrament; does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo affirm, that Chriſt ſpake of receiving his Body in <hi>Truth</hi> only, when he ſaid, <hi>He that eateth my Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. it ſeems evidently to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that when St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> wrote theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, he did not underſtand thoſe places in St. <hi>John</hi> of Sacramental Eating. Finally, by comparing this place with the former, it is plain alſo, that to eat and drink Chriſt <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually,</hi> and to eat and drink him in <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reality,</hi> was in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Judgment all one; and conſequently that we may <hi>really</hi> eat the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt, and drink his <hi>Blood,</hi> though we do it not <hi>corporeally.</hi> Theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of this Father I have the rather inſiſted upon, becauſe I have affirmed in the Notes, that he would not allow that a wicked Man is <hi>truly</hi> a partaker of the Body and Blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> which is evident from theſe Paſſages, tho I have produced them chiefly to ſhew what his moſt deliberate Thoughts were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſenſe of the ſixth Chapter of St. <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But after all, though I verily think that I could make out a Title to the Conſent of <hi>All the Fathers,</hi> with vaſtly more probability than thoſe who claim it for the other Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:40809:13"/> yet, ſuppoſe that they have theſe three that are cited laſt, and as many more as they can name with any colour; what would they get by it, if notwithſtanding theſe Fathers did not believe that the Natural Fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>properly</hi> eaten, and his Blood <hi>properly</hi> drank by the Faithful in the <hi>Euchariſt?</hi> What if they believed the Subſtance of Bread and Wine to remain in the Sacrament, and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf could be fed upon by the Mind only; and therefore that theſe words them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man,</hi> &amp;c. though ſpoken of the Sacrament, were not properly but figuratively to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood? If this be ſo, they have loſt their main Cauſe, and have taken a great deal of pains to be where they were at firſt; and this Diſpute, whether the Church has always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> to be directly intended by our Saviour in the mentioned Paſſages, is loſt as to any Advantage that Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can get by it.</p>
                  <p>That the Subſtance of Bread and Wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main after Conſecration, is manifeſt from<note n="(r)" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Caecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is fed upon by the Mind only, from<note n="(s)" place="margin">In Iſai. cap. 3.</note> St <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> to whom I refer you, that I may not be over-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious; eſpecially ſince for the preſent one Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> may ſerve the turn. Obſerve therefore theſe words of his, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:40809:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Expoſition of Scripture-Phraſes;<note n="(t)" place="margin">Si praeceptiva eſt locutio aut flagitium aut facinus vetans, aut be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficentiam jubens non eſt Figurata. Si autem Flagitium aut Facinus videtur juberi, aut utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem aut beneficenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vetare Figurata eſt. Niſi manducaveritis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, carnem filii homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; ſanguinem bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beritis, vitam in vobis non habebitis, Facinus vel Flagitium videtur Jubere, Figura ergo eſt praecipiens Paſſioni Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini eſſe communican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, &amp; ſuaviter atque utiliter in memoriâ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condendum, quod caro ejus pro nobis crucifixa &amp; vulnerata ſit. <hi>De Doctrinâ Chriſtianâ, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>If the Saying be precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, either forbidding a wicked Action, or commanding to do that which is good, it is no figurative ſaying. But if it ſeems to command any Villany or Wickedneſs, or to forbid what is profitable and good, it is Figurative. This ſaying, Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you; ſeems to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a villanous or wicked thing. It is therefore a FI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE, enjoyning us to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in the Paſſion of our Lord, and to lay it up in dear and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble remembrance, that his Fleſh was crucified and wounded for our ſakes.</hi> The vaſt pains that have been taken to avoid this Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, are a convincing Argument that Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice may grow to that ſtrength, as to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible. You will confeſs, I doubt not, that this Paſſage ſo plainly ſhews St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion in this matter, that as it needs no words to illuſtrate it, ſo it is capable of no Anſwer to the purpoſe.</p>
                  <pb n="xxiv" facs="tcp:40809:14"/>
                  <p>To come to a Concluſion. As I have ſhewn that ſeveral Fathers did not underſtand the mentioned Words of our Saviour, as ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> ſo I could ſhew, that very many Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have declared againſt it; amongſt whom Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> for his ſingular Merit, and becauſe I have referred to his Reaſons in my Notes, ought to be particularly remembred. In his Commentary upon <hi>V.</hi> 53. <hi>Verily verily I ſay,</hi> &amp;c. he comes to ſpeak of a third Sence, <hi>viz.</hi> of Sacramental eating by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receivers; <hi>And,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Sence is this:</hi> 
                     <q>Except ye really eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man in the Sacrament of the Hoſt, and drink his Blood in the Sacrament of the Chalice, you have no Life in you. So that according to this ſence, not only the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> but the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> alſo, <hi>under both kinds,</hi> is neceſſary to Salvation. But the uſage of the Church is repugnant to this ſence, ſince ſhe does not give the Communion to Infants at all, nor to the People under both kinds; and not only the Uſage, but the Doctrine of the Church too, becauſe ſhe teaches that 'tis ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to Salvation, to communicate under the Species of Bread. And tho' this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be ſufficient to ſhew that the Text does not deliver a Precept of receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in both kinds, and conſequently that it
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:40809:14"/> 
                        <hi>does not deliver a Precept of eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacrament of the Euchariſt;</hi> yet the <hi>Bohemians</hi>—are not ſatisfied, but produce this Text for themſelves againſt our Uſage and Doctrine, ſaying, That if our Lord had not treated of receiving the Sacrament in theſe words, he would not have diſtinguiſhed between <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> leaſt of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween eating the <hi>Fleſh</hi> and drinking the <hi>Blood;</hi> but ſince he ſo accurately diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth between theſe things, he inſinuates his Diſcourſe to be concerning the reception of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> &amp;c. But, <hi>ſays the Cardinal,</hi> theſe things are eaſily thrown off; by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that in this very Chapter <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaid not long before, <hi>He that cometh to me ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth in me ſhall never thirst.</hi> For in theſe words which, 'tis plain, do not belong to the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> our Lord plainly diſtinguiſhes <hi>Hunger</hi> from <hi>Thirſt,</hi> which is equivalent to his diſtinction between <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking.</hi> For <hi>Hunger</hi> refers to <hi>eating,</hi> and <hi>Thirſt</hi> to <hi>drinking.</hi> Therefore from the diſtinction between eating and drinking, no ſolid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be drawn to infer the Diſcourſe to be of the Sacrament of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> In like manner the diſtinction between <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> availeth nothing to their purpoſe, but rather againſt them; becauſe the Fleſh is not diſtinguiſhed from the Blood after any
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:40809:15"/> ſort, but only as they are ſeparated, as <hi>Meat</hi> from <hi>Drink.</hi> But 'tis evident that the real ſeparation of the Fleſh and Blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Sacrament, is <hi>repreſented</hi> only: But in the Death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> it was actual, and <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the thing</hi> it ſelf. And if it be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that the Fleſh and the Blood are here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of under the Notion of <hi>Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> and not according to what they were in <hi>their own Nature,</hi> and that for this reaſon, the Diſcourſe runs upon the <hi>Fleſh</hi> in the Sacrament, and the <hi>Blood</hi> in the Sacrament, <hi>ſeparated</hi> one from another. The Anſwer to this is afforded by what has been already ſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> that our Lord had ſpoken of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before, as of one that takes away Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and of one that takes away Thirſt; and yet 'tis not alſo inferred from hence, that he ſpake of himſelf as under that <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> whereby he takes away Hunger, and that <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament</hi> whereby he takes away Thirſt. For he diſcourſes of the Fleſh and Blood,<note n="†" place="margin">Partibus mortis ſuae.</note> which are parted at his Death, as they are to be embraced by the Mind, being the <hi>Meat and Drink of the Soul:</hi> Becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs our Spirit be ſuſtained by the Death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as by Meat, and be delighted with it as with Drink, there is not the Life of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in us.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:40809:15"/>
                  <p>And now, <hi>Sir,</hi> having given you ſo large an Account of this great Man's Opinion in his own Words, I ſhall content my ſelf to ſay in general, that if it were needful, others might be produced for the ſame; even Popes, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Biſhops and Doctors, who (as far as I can diſcern) were for number, as well as qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, not inferiour to thoſe who maintained the contrary ſide before the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, that Council it ſelf would have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter informed thoſe that told you, the Church has ſtill underſtood this part of the Chapter as treating of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> There were warm Diſcourſes in the <hi>Congregation</hi> between the Divines, concerning the Interpretation of theſe Paſſages: But at laſt it was concluded, neither to affirm or deny them to be meant of the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> but it was agreed however to deny, that the neceſſity of communicating in both kinds could be inferred, ſuppoſing that the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> was meant; that is to ſay, it was carried by the Majority: And to gratifie thoſe that thought it was not meant, it was to be acknowledged that they had Fathers and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of their Opinion. For the Matter, all things conſidered, was accommodated as well as it could be in theſe words;<note n="(u)" place="margin">Sed neque ex Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone illo apud Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſexto recte coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur utriuſque ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i communionem à Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Praecepram eſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque juxta varias ſanctorum Patrum &amp; Doctorum Interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes inteliigatur. <hi>Conc. Trid. Seſſ</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Nor from that Diſcourſe in the</hi> 6th <hi>of St.</hi> John <hi>is it rightly gathered, that the
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:40809:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Communion of both kinds was enjoined by our Lord; however that Diſcourſe be underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the various Interpretations of the Holy Fathers and Doctors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I doubt I have ſaid more than enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſhort intimation of that Pretence, that <hi>the Church</hi> has always interpreted theſe places of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> But I hope you will make this conſtruction of it, that I am one of thoſe who bear a due regard to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Tradition of the Univerſal Church, as I believe you to be another. For which Reaſon I thought it more needful to remove ſo great a Prejudice out of your way, as the belief of the foreſaid Inſinuation would have been. And I am confident you now ſee that in maintaining the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> not to be intended by our Saviour in any part of this Chapter, any more than other parts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, I am not obliged to encounter the Authority of <hi>All</hi> the Ancients, or of the <hi>whole</hi> Church; nay, that in this matter I do not ſo much as entrench upon the Authority of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Indeed that Council would have me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that not one of the various Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Fathers and Doctors, makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Communion in one kind. But I hope I may be excuſed, if I can believe that which ſeveral Men of high Rank in their own Church were not able to believe.</p>
                  <pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:40809:16"/>
                  <p>And as for that Doctrine, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is properly eaten in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> I ought to be excuſed too, if I can by no means believe it; or elſe thoſe Fathers muſt be condemned, who believed the <hi>Capernaites</hi> to be a perverſe ſort of Men, for turning our Saviour's words in this Chapter, to ſo inhumane and abſurd a ſenſe, as if he had exhorted them to eat a Man's Fleſh, according to the propriety of thoſe words. For no Man can ſay, that this is either inhumane or abſurd, who believes the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is properly eaten in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that for what I can ſee, this Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> inſtead of affording a ſolid Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that Concluſion, when it comes to be well conſidered upon the Grounds of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Authority, does at laſt yield a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Objection againſt it.</p>
                  <p>I have thought of all theſe Things, with the liberty of one that loves Truth, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due regard to the Ancient Doctors of the Church. Our common Maſter hath taught me, <hi>to call no man Maſter upon Earth;</hi> yet I never refuſed the help of his <hi>Miniſters</hi> to guide me into the knowledge of this Truth: And ſince I have been able to uſe that help, I have ſtill valued, in the firſt place, that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance which is offered me from the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:40809:17"/> Biſhops and Fathers. And this Liberty I have been encouraged to uſe in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not only for judging of Points which ſhe has not determined, but thoſe alſo which ſhe has. And from the bottom of my heart I give thanks to Almighty God, that I have had my Education in the Communion of a Church, which at the ſame time that it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to me a Rule of Doctrine and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, does give me full liberty to enquire all manner of ways, whether ſhe has dealt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely with me or not. Under the Diſcipline of ſo honeſt a Church, I truſt that I have learn'd to be an honeſt Man. For though I am as confident of the main Queſtion as I deſire to be, yet I have, and by the Grace of God always will have, a quiet Reſerve for better Information: And I ſhall not count him an Enemy but a Friend, that both can and will diſcover my Miſtakes. For which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I have obeyed your Advice, and asked the leave of my Superiors, to let theſe plain Thoughts go into the World. And I let them go, much rather deſiring that they may meet with Contradiction, than Approbation in any part, where they ought to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted.</p>
                  <p>Nay, I will not refuſe to make allowance for them who cannot oppoſe an Adverſary without Huffing and Vanity. If I can ſee that they offer, though but a little Reaſon, I will
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:40809:17"/> readily acknowledge it; or if they offer none at all, let them but ſeem to believe what they ſay, and they ſhall not go without a Reply.</p>
                  <p>As for that Senſe which I have (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Authority) offered, of thoſe Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in this Chapter concerning the <hi>Father's drawing,</hi> and <hi>giving</hi> Men to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> if it does not equally pleaſe all Perſons, I hope they who are otherwiſe minded will not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with me, when I have declared, that I ſhall no longer care for it, when any Man ſhall lead my Underſtanding to a better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sir,</hi> I have but one thing more to ſay; Let you and I obſerve and follow the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inſtructions of this Chapter; which if all would do, I am confident none of us ſhould run into any dangerous Miſtake about the meaning of any part of it. Our Lord hath ſaid it: That <hi>if any man will do his Will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine whether it be of God.</hi> In paraphraſing our Saviour's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes here, I could not but obſerve how apt it was to infuſe a truly wiſe, honeſt and godly Temper into the Minds of his Hearers. And therefore for a Concluſion, I added to the Paraphraſe what I thought was a ſuitable Exhortation; that whilſt we may happen to diſpute about the ſenſe of ſome
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:40809:18"/> more difficult Paſſages in this Chapter, we may not forget to make the great Deſign of it the Subject of our Practice. And ſo I commend you to the Grace of God, and reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40809:18"/>
                  <head>The Sixth Chapter of St. JOHN.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The ARGUMENT.</head>
                  <p>This Chapter begins with a Narrative of the miraculous feeding of Five Thouſand in the Wilderneſs, and conſiſteth wholly of thoſe Paſſages that happened upon this occaſion. The People were ſo overjoyed with the Miracle, that they reſolved to make <hi>Jeſus</hi> a King; which he avoided, and ſecretly went to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum.</hi> But they not ſo ſatisfied, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him thither the next day; when he took another courſe to prevent their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; and that by reproving their worldly-mindedneſs, and by calling them off from the Cares and Pleaſures of this Life, to mind Heavenly Things, and everlaſting Life; which ſo turned their Stomachs againſt him, that they fell to cavil at his Sayings, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage his Miracles, by ſetting up the <hi>Manna</hi> wherewith <hi>Moſes</hi> had fed their Fathers,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40809:19"/> againſt his feeding them the day before. Whereupon he inculcated two things upon them with great Earneſtneſs: The one was this, That they might gain eternal Life by Him and his Doctrine; which he therefore called the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> and <hi>the Bread that came down from Heaven;</hi> and therefore that it was a vain thing in them to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge him with <hi>Moſes</hi>'s giving their Fathers that Bread from Heaven, which ſerved only to ſuſtain a mortal Life. The other was this, That they had ſufficient Evidence of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God; but that they believed not, becauſe of their worldly Prejudices againſt him. Whereupon he tells them, that God had committed no other Perſons to his effectual Care, to convince and ſave them, but ſuch only who were diſpoſed to receive the Truth by an honeſt Mind; and that himſelf was not bound to conquer the obſtinacy of unteachable Men. Notwithſtanding all which, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to cavil at his Sayings; and becauſe, in alluſion to the Loaves he had multiplied, and to that <hi>Manna</hi> which they boaſted of, he had called himſelf the <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> and in purſuance of ſuch Figurative Speeches, he did alſo expreſs believing in him, and truſting in his Death, <hi>&amp;c. by eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood:</hi> They exclaimed againſt him, as if he had, in the literal ſenſe, offered his Fleſh to be eaten: ſome of his own Diſciples alſo underſtanding him in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40809:19"/> that manner: To whom indeed he explained himſelf: But for all that, upon his free Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of their inſincerity, they left him. And then he proved the Conſtancy of his Twelve Apoſtles, permitting them alſo to go, if they were not willing to ſtay: ſhewing withal, that he underſtood who were ſincere, and who were not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>The Chapter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 1.</hi> AFter theſe things Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus went over the Sea of Galilee, which is the Sea of <hi>Tiberias.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40809:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 2.</hi> And a great multitude follow'd him, becauſe they ſaw his Miracles which he did upon them that were diſeaſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 3.</hi> And Jeſus went up into a Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and there he ſat with his Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 4.</hi> And the Paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, a Feaſt of the Jews, was nigh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 5.</hi> When Jeſus then lift up his eyes, and ſaw a great compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny come to him, he ſaith unto Philip, Whence ſhall we buy bread that theſe may eat?</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40809:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 6.</hi> And this he ſaid to prove him: for he himſelf knew what he would do)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 7.</hi> Philip anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, Two hundred penny-worth of bread is not ſufficient for them, that every one of them may take a little.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 8.</hi> One of his Diſciples, Andrew, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peters Brother, ſaith unto him,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 9.</hi> There is a lad here, which hath five barley loaves, and two ſmall fiſhes; but what are they among ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 10.</hi> And Jeſus ſaid, Make the men ſit down. Now there was much graſs in the place. So that men ſat down
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40809:21"/> in number about five thouſand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 11.</hi> And Jeſus took the loaves, and when he had given thanks, he diſtributed to the Diſciples, and the Diſciples to them that were ſet down, and likewiſe of the fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es as much as they would.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 12.</hi> When they were filled, he ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the fragments that remain that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be loſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 13.</hi> Therefore they gathered them together, and filled twelve Baskets with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40809:21"/> the fragments of the five barley loaves, which remained over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove unto them that had eaten.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 14.</hi> Then thoſe men, when they had ſeen the miracle which Jeſus did, ſaid, This is of a truth that Prophet which was to come into the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 15.</hi> When Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus therefore perceived that they would come and take him by force, to make him a King, he departed again into a mountain himſelf alone.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40809:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 16.</hi> And when Even was now come, his Diſciples went down unto the Sea,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 17.</hi> And entred into a Ship, and went over the Sea, towards Capernaum, and it was now dark, and Jeſus was not come to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 18.</hi> And the Sea aroſe by reaſon of a great wind that blew.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 19.</hi> So when they had rowed about five and twenty or thirty furlongs, they ſee Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus walking on the Sea, and drawing nigh unto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40809:22"/> the Ship: and they were afraid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 20.</hi> But he ſaith unto them, It is I, be not afraid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 21.</hi> Then they willingly received him into the Ship, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately the Ship was at the land whither they went.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 22.</hi> The day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which ſtood on the other ſide of the Sea, ſaw that there was no other boat there, ſave that one whereinto his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were entred, and that Jeſus went not with his Diſciples into the Boat, but that his Diſciples were gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way alone:</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40809:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 23.</hi> (Howbeit, there came other boats from Tiberias, nigh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place where they did eat bread, after that the Lord had giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Thanks:)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 24.</hi> When the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therefore ſaw that Jeſus was not there, neither his Diſciples, they alſo took ſhipping, and came to Caperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſeeking for Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 25.</hi> And when they had found him on the other ſide of the Sea, they ſaid unto him, Rabbi, when ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thou hither?</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40809:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 26.</hi> Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them and ſaid, Verily, verily I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Ye ſeek me, not becauſe ye ſaw the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles but becauſe ye did eat of the loaves, and were filled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 27.</hi> Labour not for the meat which periſheth, but for that meat which endureth to everlaſting life; which the Son of Man ſhall give unto you: for him hath God the Father ſealed.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40809:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 28.</hi> Then ſaid they unto him, What ſhall we do, that we might work the works of God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 29.</hi> Jeſus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid unto them, This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 30.</hi> They ſaid therefore unto him, What ſign ſheweſt thou then, that we may ſee,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40809:24"/> and believe thee? what doſt thou work?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="paraphrase">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40809:19"/>
                  <head>The Paraphraſe.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I Shall not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles which <hi>Jeſus</hi> wrought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Paſſover laſt mentioned, [<hi>Ch.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 1.] and that which was now at hand, [<hi>v.</hi> 4. of this <hi>Ch.</hi>] ſaving that only of the <hi>Loaves;</hi> which though it be reported by all the other <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> yet they have omitted that Diſcourſe upon it which he had with the <hi>Jews.</hi> The occaſion of it was this: He went in a Boat with his Diſciples over that part of the Lake of <hi>Genezareth</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> which waſheth the City <hi>Tiberias.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40809:20"/>2. And a great multitude followed him on foot, [<hi>Mat.</hi> 14.13.] through <hi>Tiberias,</hi> ſome of them being diſeaſed Perſons, whom he cured in the Deſert where they overtook him, [<hi>Luke</hi> 11.11.]</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And he took his Diſciples with him to a Mountain in that Deſert to inſtruct them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But the People now haſtning from all parts towards <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eruſalem,</hi> becauſe of the approaching Paſſover.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Company that came to <hi>Jeſus</hi> in this Deſert place, was greatly encreaſed; which he obſerving, was deſired by his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> to ſpeak to them to depart, and to provide for themſelves: Whereupon he ſaid to <hi>Philip,</hi> Doſt thou think it poſſible to procure Meat for this Multitude in the Wilderneſs?</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40809:20"/>6. (Which he ſaid not that he was at a loſs what to do, but to prove the Faith of the Man, who was none of the forwardeſt to believe,) [<hi>Ch.</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 9.]</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Philip</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a Miracle, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, All the Stock we have will not buy Bread enough for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of theſe ſo much as to taſte a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of.</p>
                  <p n="8">8, 9. But <hi>Andrew</hi> preſently interpoſed, ſaying, That they had five Loaves and two ſmall Fiſhes; by which he ſeemed to expect that his Maſter would do ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary thing, but what he knew not, the Proviſion being ſo very little.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Then <hi>Jeſus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Twelve, to diſpoſe the Men in order upon the graſs, of which there was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40809:21"/> great plenty at that time of the year, [ſee <hi>v.</hi> 4.] and ſo they did, (not diſtruſting the Event) and found the Men to be about five thouſand.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. And when <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> had bleſſed the little Food that was there, by thanking the Great Creator and Preſerver of all things; he with his own hands delivered ſo many Portions of it to the Twelve, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves to adminiſter to the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: And the Bread and the Fiſh were ſo marvellouſly encreaſed as it went through their hands, that every one of that great Company had as much as he deſired to eat.</p>
                  <p n="12, 13">12, 13. And when they acknowledged that they had eaten enough, he bad the Twelve, <hi>gather up the Fragments,</hi> &amp;c. And every one of them filled his Basket with what was left; ſo that there were twelve
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40809:21"/> Baskets full of broken Food, which was an evidence of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionableneſs of the Miracle, and that no juggle had been put upon the Peoples Stomachs, ſince there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſo much to be ſeen after they had all eaten.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. And this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle was ſo plain, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Belly filled with it, that they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to mind [<hi>v.</hi> 31.] how <hi>Moſes</hi> gave their Fathers <hi>Manna</hi> in the Wilderneſs, and foretold that God would raiſe up a Prophet like unto him out of their Brethren; and now they concluded that this was that Prophet, and the Perſon that was to deliver them from the <hi>Romans,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their Forefathers from the <hi>Egyptians, &amp;c.</hi> ſince he, as well as <hi>Moſes,</hi> could, in the greateſt Extremity ſupply them with what Proviſion they ſhould need.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. And of this they talked ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently, that at laſt they reſolved to make him King, whether he would or not;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40809:22"/> which <hi>Jeſus</hi> perceiving, he firſt ſent away his own Diſciples, almoſt forcing them into the Boat that brought them thither, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be with them before they came to the other ſide, [<hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Mark</hi> 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.] And being thus rid of his Diſciples, who were pleaſed with the Reſolution of the People, and ready enough to join with them in it, he more eaſily ſatisfied and diſperſed the Multitude: and ſo without any Followers he returned to the Mountain to pray by himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Now is was juſt about the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples came down to the Shore.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. And entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Boat to go over towards <hi>Capernaum;</hi> but it grew very dark before <hi>Jeſus</hi> came to them.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. And the Sea alſo was tempeſtuous with a contrary Wind, [<hi>Mark</hi> 6.48.]</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Inſomuch that their Sails being a hindrance to to them, they laboured hard with their Oars; and yet by the fourth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40809:22"/> Watch of the Night they had not gained above 25, or 30 Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs; when they ſaw <hi>Jeſus</hi> walking upon the Sea, as if he were paſſing by the Ship; and not yet knowing him, they took him for an Apparition, and were afraid, [<hi>Mat.</hi> 14.26.]</p>
                  <p n="20, 21">20, 21. But when they knew him, they received him gladly, believing that all things would go well now he was with them: and ſo it proved: For though they had made ſo little Progreſs before, yet now the Ship came preſently to the place whither it was bound.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. Now the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom <hi>Jeſus</hi> had fed in the Deſert, were not ſo perfectly diſperſed, but that many of them kept together till the day following, and came to the Shore where the Diſciples took Ship the Evening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and although
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40809:23"/> they knew there was no other Boat there, when the Diſciples went to Sea, but that into which they entred, and that <hi>Jeſus</hi> did not go with them.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. (Tho' there came other Boats from <hi>Tiberias</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, which theſe Men found that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, near the place where the Miracle was wrought:)</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Yet knowing that the Diſciples were gone, and not being able to find <hi>Jeſus</hi> on that ſide, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he was gone after them, tho' they knew not how, [<hi>v.</hi> 25.] And ſo they reſolved to follow the Diſciples in thoſe Boats that were newly come from <hi>Tiberias,</hi> hoping to find <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf with them at <hi>Capernaum</hi> or <hi>Bethſaida.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="25">25. And when they found him, they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to know by what Miracle he got thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo ſoon, for they knew he went not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with his Diſciples, and no other Boat was on the other ſide to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40809:23"/> tranſport him, but thoſe in which they came and the way by Land, over the Bridge of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berias,</hi> was too far about to get thither in ſo ſhort a time.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. But <hi>Jeſus,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſatisfying their curioſity in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, turned the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to things of greater moment, and anſwered them in this manner: I certainly know that ye do not follow me for the true end of thoſe Miracles which I work; which is, that ye might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in me, and obtain everlaſting Life; but meerly for that preſent Benefit, which you hope to receive by them, as you did yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, when you <hi>did eat, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="27">27. But I had a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end in feeding your Bodies, which now I require you to mind; and that is, to perſwade you not to take ſo much pains for the prolonging of a Life which will ſhortly end, as for that Vertue and Knowledge which are the <hi>Food of Souls,</hi> and the means of living happily for ever, when this Life ſhall be no more. You
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40809:24"/> ſhould follow the Son of Man for ſuch things as theſe, the Father having ſhewed him to be the Perſon who ſhould convey theſe Bleſſings to the Souls of Men, and that by thoſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works which he hath ſent him to do for the relief of their Bodies.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. Theſe Men were ſo ſuddainly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſted with this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Doctrine, that they replied in this manner, We who have the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> do already know what Works God requires; And canſt thou tell us, what will be more pleaſing to him than our keeping of the Law?</p>
                  <p n="29">29. <hi>Jeſus</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God hath ſent his Son into the World, to reveal a better Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and to preſcribe a better Life than <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did: And that Work pleaſing to God, and neceſſary to your Salvation, which you muſt do, is in ſhort this, To believe him whom God hath ſent, and to take his Word for your Security, in doing all that he requires.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. But they were ſo ſtrangely prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his calling them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40809:24"/> off from the Cares of this World to a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Life, and a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Hope, that the late Miracle for which they had ſo extolled him, [<hi>v.</hi> 14.] was now in their Opinion nothing at all: And ſo they replied to him, as if they had ſaid; If thou pretendeſt to a higher Doctrine than <hi>Moſes</hi> taught, why doſt not thou ſhew us equal, if not greater Signs and Wonders than he wrought, that we may <hi>ſee</hi> them, and <hi>believe</hi> thee for their ſake? What doſt thou perform anſwerable to ſuch a mighty Faith, as thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt of us?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notes">
                  <head>NOTES.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 30. This ſuddain Turn of theirs was ſo ſtrange, that <hi>Grotius</hi> does not allow thoſe that ſaid this to be the ſame Perſons that were fed in the Wilderneſs the day before. But I can ſee no reaſon for his Opinion; for the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt</hi> plainly ſeems to continue the Relation, as of the ſame Perſons; and it is no unuſual thing for Men either to keep or alter their Perſwaſions, as they are led by their Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices and Intereſts. And our Saviour told thoſe that had been fed in the Wilderneſs, that they followed him for worldly Advantages, and not for Inſtruction in Spiritual and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly matters, <hi>v.</hi> 26. So that finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40809:25"/> diſappointed, it was not unlikely that they would fall in their Opinion of him. To which we may add, that one main Deſign of his following Diſcourſe was to ſhew, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Evidence was not ſufficient to create Faith, without the inward preparation of a ſincere and honeſt Mind: Which was very pertinent to the Caſe of thoſe Men who were made confident that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was <hi>that Prophet,</hi> by the late Miracle, till they found that his Doctrine was contrary to their worldly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. For which reaſons I have choſe to continue the Diſcourſe in the Paraphraſe, as the Text ſeems to direct, <hi>i. e.</hi> between <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the ſame Perſons that ſpake to him, <hi>v.</hi> 25. rather than to ſubſtitute other Speakers, for which there is neither Authority of the Text, nor any need upon the account of avoiding inconvenience.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 31.</hi> Our Fathers did eat Manna in the Deſert; as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, He gave them Bread from Heaven to eat.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40809:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 32.</hi> Then Jeſus ſaid unto them, Verily verily I ſay unto you, Moſes gave you not that Bread from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but my Father giveth you the true Bread from Heaven.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 33.</hi> For the Bread of God is he that cometh down from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40809:26"/> Heaven, and giveth life unto the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 34.</hi> Then ſaid they unto him, Lord, evermore give us this Bread.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40809:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 35.</hi> And Jeſus ſaid unto them, I am the Bread of Life: He that cometh to me, ſhall never hunger; and he that believeth in me, ſhall never thirſt.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40809:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 36.</hi> But I ſaid unto you, that ye alſo have ſeen me, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not?</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40809:27"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 37.</hi> All that the Father giveth me, ſhall come to me; and him that cometh to me, I will in no wiſe caſt out.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40809:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 38.</hi> For I came down from Heaven, not to do my own Will, but the Will of him that ſent me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 39.</hi> And this is the Father's Will which hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up again at the last day.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40809:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 40.</hi> And this is the Will of him that ſent me, that every one which ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlaſting life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:40809:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 41.</hi> The Jews then murmured at him, becauſe he ſaid, I am the Bread which came down from Heaven.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40809:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 42.</hi> And they ſaid, Is not this Jeſus the ſon of Joſeph, whoſe Father and Mother we know? how is it then that he ſaith, I came down from Heaven?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 43.</hi> Jeſus there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwered and ſaid unto them, Murmur not among your ſelves.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40809:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 44.</hi> No man can come to me, except the Father which hath ſent me, draw him: and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40809:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 45.</hi> It is written in the Prophets, And they ſhall be all taught of God. Every man therefore that hath heard, and hath learned of the Father, cometh unto me.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40809:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 46.</hi> Not that any man hath ſeen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſave he which is of God, he hath ſeen the Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 47.</hi> Verily veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſay unto you, He that believeth on me hath everlaſting Life.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40809:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 48.</hi> I am that Bread of Life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 49.</hi> Your Fathers did eat Manna in the Wilderneſs, and are dead.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 50.</hi> This is the Bread which cometh down from Heaven, that a man may eat thereof, and not die.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40809:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 51.</hi> I am the living Bread, which came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: If any man Eat of this Bread, he ſhall live for ever: and the Bread that I will give, is my Fleſh, which I will give for the Life of the world.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40809:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 52.</hi> The Jews therefore ſtrove amongſt themſelves, ſaying, How can this Man give us his Fleſh to eat?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 53.</hi> Then Jeſus ſaid unto them, Verily verily I ſay unto you, Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of Man, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40809:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 54.</hi> Whoſo eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Blood, hath eternal Life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40809:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 55.</hi> For my Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40809:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 56.</hi> He that eateth my Fleſh and drinketh my Blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40809:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 57.</hi> As the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father: ſo, he that eateth me, even he ſhall live by me.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40809:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 58.</hi> This is that Bread which came down from Heaven: not as your Fathers did eat Manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this Bread ſhall live for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40809:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 59.</hi> Theſe things ſaid he in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, as he taught in Capernaum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 60.</hi> Many there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of his Diſciples, when they had heard this, ſaid, This is an hard ſaying, who can bear it?</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:40809:43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 61.</hi> When Jeſus knew in himſelf that his Diſciples murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at it, he ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Doth this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 62.</hi> What and if ye ſhall ſee the Son of Man aſcend up where he was before?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 63.</hi> It is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that quickneth, the Fleſh profiteth nothing; The words that I ſpeak
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40809:44"/> unto you, they are Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and they are Life.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:40809:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 64.</hi> But there are ſome of you that believe not. For Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus knew from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, who they were that believed not, and who ſhould betray him.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40809:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 65.</hi> And he ſaid, Therefore ſaid I unto you, that no man can come unto me, except it were given unto him of my Father.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 66.</hi> From that time many of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples went back, and walked no more with him.</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40809:46"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 67.</hi> Then ſaid Jeſus unto the Twelve, Will ye alſo go away?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 68.</hi> Then Simon Peter anſwered him, Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou hast the words of eternal life.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40809:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 69.</hi> And we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and are ſure that thou art that Chriſt the Son of the living God.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40809:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 70.</hi> Jeſus anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, Have not I choſen you Twelve, and one of you is a Devil?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 71.</hi> He ſpake of Judas Iſcariot the Son of Simon: for he it was that ſhould betray him, being one of the Twelve.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <p n="31">31. 'Tis true, that in our need thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt us Bread to eat, making five Loaves to ſerve above five thouſand of us. But what was this to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes's</hi> feeding our Fathers in the Deſert, who were vaſtly many more, and this Forty years, with <hi>Manna</hi> alſo, which was not earthly Food, ſuch as we are yeſterday, but <hi>Bread from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> as we are taught in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.25.</p>
                  <p n="32">
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:40809:25"/>32. Now the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that <hi>Jeſus</hi> made to this, ſuppoſed that theſe Men wanted not evidence of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God; and that they ought not to compare the <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> which their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ate, with the Bread that he had given them the day before, but rather with that ineſtimable Bleſſing which God had now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them, in giving his own Son for the Life of the World: And in this he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued his conſtant Deſign, of taking off their Affections from Worldly, and directing them to Heavenly Things. For he anſwered them to this effect: Whereas you magnifie. <hi>Moſes</hi> for giving your Fathers <hi>Bread from Heaven,</hi> I tell you, it came not from <hi>that Heaven</hi> which is the place of Immortality, but only from that Region of the Air; which, though it be alſo called <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſhall at laſt periſh with the Earth. But now God offereth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that which, in the moſt excellent ſenſe, is Heavenly Bread, and which indeed comes from the place where his Majeſty dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. Whereas alſo you extol <hi>Moſes</hi> for preſerving the Lives
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40809:26"/> of your Fathers in the Wilderneſs, ſo long as he did: you may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it was but a <hi>ſhort</hi> Life at longeſt, which that Bread ſerved to ſuſtain. But he whom God hath now ſent from Heaven, is indeed, and deſires therefore to be called the True Bread, becauſe he can preſerve you to <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Life. And Laſtly, the Bread which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> gave your Fathers, did indeed ſerve a great many; yet they were but a <hi>very few</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, for that which I ſpeak of, is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to give Eternal Life to the <hi>whole World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="34">34. They replied hereupon; We deſire no other, Bread than this which thou ſo highly magnifieſt, give us but ſuch Bread always as this, and without all queſtion we ſhall believe thee.</p>
                  <p n="34">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 34. They are ſtill the ſame Perſons that ſpeak, for there is yet no reaſon to ſuppoſe the contrary. And by this ſaying, it ſeems they underſtood <hi>Jeſus</hi> as if he had ſpoken to them of Bread from Heaven, in the literal and groſs ſence, and by giving that to 'em, from day to day, had promiſed to make them live for ever: So that from his laſt Words they ſeemed to conceive ſome better hope of him again, and that he would go on to fill their Bellies every day. Therefore they ſpake
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40809:26"/> to him now with more reſpect. So hard it was even for <hi>Jeſus</hi> to bring them to any underſtanding, or ſence of things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned their Minds, though he would lead them thereunto, by alluſion to things grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their Senſes. And this indeed was the general Temper of the <hi>Jews</hi> in our Saviour's days, who were alſo in this reſpect rather worſe than their Fore-fathers. It was juſt ſuch another Anſwer that the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man made to a like Speech of our Lord, as you may ſee <hi>Ch.</hi> 4. 5, 13, 14, 15.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. <hi>Jeſus</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, If you underſtand me aright, you have your Wiſh. I do not now diſcourſe of thoſe Signs which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee, before you believe, (for you have already had Signs in abundance) but of the far greater Benefits which you will gain by believing in me, than your Fathers had from <hi>Moſes.</hi> I tell you therefore, that I am the Bread of Everlaſting Life; and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in me, and ſubmitteth to my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, hath the Bread and Water of Life, and ſhall hunger and thirſt no more; for he ſhall need no other means of obtaining Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life, than to become my Diſciple.</p>
                  <p n="36">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40809:27"/>36. Do not think that I take that for granted which I ought to prove, for you have already ſeen enough to convince you that I ſpeak the Truth. But as I told you before, (<hi>ver.</hi> 26.) Signs and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles will not work true Faith in you, ſo long as you follow me for Temporal Benefits, and have not learned to prefer Spiritual good Things, and everlaſting Life, above Meat and Drink, and all the Enjoyments of this World whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 36. Theſe Perſons, of whom our Lord ſaid that they <hi>believed not,</hi> were thoſe very Men, who the day before having <hi>ſeen the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle which he did,</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is of a truth that Prophet that ſhould come into the World:</hi> Whereby it ſhould ſeem that then they believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that their Minds were now changed, tho' upon no other reaſon, than that they now perceived his great Deſign was, to feed their Minds with good Doctrine, and not to pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per their Bodies. Which is a plain Inſtance, how great an hindrance worldly-mindedneſs is to True Faith, ſince in this Caſe, the ſame Evidence which convinced theſe Men, while they took our Saviour to be a Benefactor to their <hi>Bodies,</hi> had loſt all its force with them, when they once perceived that his great Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was, to ſave their <hi>Souls.</hi> Some alſo of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40809:27"/> our Lord's Diſciples were of this Diſpoſition; and it had the ſame effect upon them, as you may ſee <hi>v.</hi> 64.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. So that the reaſon why you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me not, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by a good and honeſt Heart to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Truth. And now I tell you, that the Father, who would have all to be ſaved, does not expect that I ſhould give a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of any other Perſons, but ſuch as are of a towardly and teachable Diſpoſition. Theſe he hath committed to my ſpecial care; and they will learn of me, and not one of them ſhall want means requiſite for his Conviction and Inſtruction. But though I came to ſave the World, (<hi>v.</hi> 51.) I am not bound to bring thoſe to Faith and to Salvation, that obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ſet themſelves againſt all that Evidence which is ſufficient for honeſt Minds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 37. It ſeems very reaſonable to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret theſe Phraſes of the Fathers, <hi>giving ſome to Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>drawing</hi> them, by what our Lord ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 26. that theſe Men followed him, <hi>becauſe they did eat of the Loaves;</hi> i. e. not from a ſincere deſire of learning the Truth, and attaining Eternal Life, but for worldly Ends: For on the one ſide, the Luſts of theſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40809:28"/> Men were the cauſe of their Unbelief; on the other ſide, our Saviour ſays, that all who are given and drawn by the Father, would believe and become his Diſciples, and none elſe: Therefore the Father <hi>gives</hi> thoſe only to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who are prepared by an honeſt Heart, and willingneſs to learn. The Phraſe is an Alluſion to what is often ſeen amongſt us, <hi>i. e.</hi> to a Man's committing the Care of educating a hopeful and promiſing Child, to a wiſe and skilful Maſter, with the expectation of having a good account of him at laſt. Not but that theſe Expreſſions alſo imply the <hi>preparations of the Heart to be from the Lord:</hi> Neither does this hinder, but that our Lord muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to have done what was fit to prepare thoſe whom he found ſo averſe as theſe Men were. [See Notes on <hi>v.</hi> 45.] But the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that if Men obſtinately perſiſted in their ſenſual and worldly Prejudices againſt the Truth, God hath provided no Remedy for ſuch Men. And therefore, as St. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> ſhews, we muſt not argue in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. If <hi>every one whom the Father draweth, or giveth, cometh to Chriſt, and none elſe, then thoſe whom the Father giveth not, are diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all Fault, and cannot juſtly be accuſed. For,</hi> ſays he, <hi>theſe are vain words and meer pretences; ſince the free Choice of our own Wills muſt go to the effecting of this Matter: For to be taught, and to believe, depends much upon our own chuſing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="38">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40809:28"/>38. For in this matter, as well as in all others, I do what is as much the Fathers Will, as my own. And I came from Heaven to do it, and cannot depart from it. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve therefore what I ſay.</p>
                  <p n="39">39. It was his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to commit to my care all Perſons of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and well-diſpoſed Minds, that not one of them ſhould be loſt, but that I ſhould do all things which would bring them to Faith and Repentance, and ſhould take care of their Salvation from the Firſt to the Laſt, even till I ſhall raiſe them from the Dead at the laſt Day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 39. Although the Wicked ſhall be raiſed up at the laſt <hi>day,</hi> by the Power of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as well as the Juſt, yet when the Reſurrection is ſimply mentioned, it is commonly underſtood of the Reſurrection to eternal Life, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Reſurrection of the Juſt. And by ſpeaking of this Reſurrection at the laſt Day, our Lord did now put them out of doubt, that he meant not to pamper their Bodies, and to take care for their Pleaſures in this Life; but that he ſpake to them of a better Life after this, and the means of attaining it.</p>
                  <p n="40">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:40809:29"/>40. For it was his Decree alſo, that every one who ſeeing the Works that I do, (<hi>v.</hi> 36.) and attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidering the Evidence, whereby it appears that I came from God, does there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon believe and follow my Doctrine; that he, I ſay, ſhould have everlaſting Life, and that I ſhould for that end raiſe him up at the laſt Day. Now as my Father doth not expect that I ſhould ſave any but thoſe that believe and obey the Goſpel; ſo neither doth he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that I ſhould bring any to Faith, but thoſe that are of teachable Diſpoſitions. But if Men obſtinately ſet themſelves to oppoſe all means of Conviction and Reformation, it was no part of the Truſt committed to me by the Father, to reclaim them notwithſtanding their incorrigibleneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 40. To <hi>ſee Jeſus,</hi> ſignifies the ſame that it does <hi>v.</hi> 36. <hi>i. e.</hi> ſeeing his Miracles, and all other Teſtimones of a Divine Authority that were diſcernable in him: Only <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeems to note an attentive conſideration of them, which is proper to ingenuous and honeſt Men, and will certainly produce Faith. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 36. may ſignifie that careleſs and ſuperficial ſight of his Works, proper to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40809:29"/> thoſe Men in whom Prejudice ſo prevailed, that they <hi>ſaw,</hi> and yet <hi>believed not.</hi> Now that our Saviour does here, and elſewhere, repeat his Doctrine concerning that <hi>inward</hi> Work of God, <hi>viz.</hi> an honeſt and godly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, is an Argument that he laid great ſtreſs upon it; and that indeed this was the main thing they were to take pains with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about. For the <hi>outward</hi> Evidence was given them whether they would or not; but the <hi>inward Preparation,</hi> without which the <hi>outward Evidence</hi> would do them no good at all, muſt in ſome part be their own Work as well as God's; which was plain, from <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s ſpeaking to them ſo much about it as he did. For if it was not their own fault that they were not inwardly prepared; and if it was impoſſible for them to do any thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable towards it, his Reproof had ſeemed ſomething unreaſonable and unjuſt; and if they had ſo underſtood it, they had not been wanting to tell him ſo.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. But the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were by no means pleaſed with what <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſaid; for they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected he would give them Bread from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as <hi>Moſes</hi> had done for their Fathers, (<hi>v.</hi> 34.) but now they plainly perceived, that by the Bread of Life coming down from Heaven,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40809:30"/> which he ſpake of, he meant Himſelf and his Doctrine, (<hi>v.</hi> 35.) and that inſtead of feeding their Bodies, he promiſed them everlaſting Life; which they were not greatly concerned about. And upon this diſappointment, they again ſet themſelves to diſparage him all they could.</p>
                  <p n="42">42. And ſaid one to another, Why does this Man, whom we know to be the Son of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> pretend ſuch high things of himſelf? How could he come from Heaven, who was born into this World as other Men are, and in as mean Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as the moſt.</p>
                  <p n="43">43. To theſe Cavils <hi>Jeſus</hi> anſwered, Do not loſe time, by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Difficulties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout my Perſon and Doctrine: There is another Work that lies upon your Hands, which is at preſent more ſeaſonable and neceſſary for you, than to ſtrain for Objections againſt what I ſay, and that is, to mend your Tempers; to ſhake off your worldly Spirits; to make eternal Life your End, and ſincerely to deſire the Knowledge of that Way which leads to it.</p>
                  <p n="44">
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40809:30"/>44. For if you are not thus qualified, all my Sayings and Works will never convince you of the Truth: For the Father did not ſend me into the World with any other Charge, than that I ſhould do what is abundantly ſufficient to ſave Men of plain Honeſty and ſincere Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which Diſpoſitions therefore you ſhould endeavour after; and if by the Grace of God you obtain them, then you will readily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and embrace the Truth. But till then you do but entangle your ſelves to no purpoſe: And therefore I adviſe you to leave off objecting and diſputing, till you have learnt plain Duties, and to become honeſt Men. And I tell you again, I will take care that no ſuch Perſons ſhall want abundant means of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and Salvation, but they ſhall be my peculiar Charge, from the time that they are ſo diſpoſed, till I ſhall raiſe them up at the laſt Day.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 44. St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> obſerves, that upon this ſaying the <hi>Manichees</hi> confidently affirmed, that nothing was in our own Power: For, ſaid they, <hi>If a man comes to him, what needs he to be drawn?</hi> But, ſays he, <hi>this does not take away all power over our own Actions, but rather ſhews that we ſtand in need of God's help; and that not every negligent Perſon, but he that takes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40809:31"/> great pains with himſelf, will come to Chriſt.</hi> The true ſence of this Verſe is more largely expreſſed in the Paraphraſe, and in Notes upon <hi>V.</hi> 37.</p>
                  <p n="45">45. And theſe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions I give you, are warranted by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> who have foretold, that when the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall begin to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed upon the Earth, Men ſhall not want any reaſonable means of Conviction for the ſaving of their Souls, becauſe God will then vouchſafe to appear more remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to inſtruct Men, than ever he did ſince the World began: And therefore if any Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in Unbelief, or refuſes to obey, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be for want of means to make him wiſe unto Salvation, but for want of an humble and an honeſt Mind, and a ſincere Intention, without which God's ſpeaking to Men, by his own Son, will have no ſucceſs upon them, but will leave them as bad as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But becauſe God is a Maſter in whom nothing can be wanting to inſtruct; every one that deſireth to know the Truth, and to be ſaved, will ſubmit to the Doctrine of his Son, and become his Diſciple.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40809:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 45. The 54th Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a Deſcription of God's gracious Care and Providence over his Church; one Inſtance whereof, <hi>v.</hi> 33. is this; <hi>And all thy Children ſhall be taught of God.</hi> Which muſt needs imply theſe two things: 1. That God would reveal that Truth which the Church ſhould profeſs; and this was eminently done by the Son of God himſelf coming down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to make it known, and by the Holy Ghoſt inſpiring the Apoſtles afterward. 2. That God would abundantly ſatisfie Men by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Teſtimonies, that he had ſent his Son into the World for that purpoſe. For theſe Reaſons, all that believe in <hi>Christ,</hi> are <hi>taught</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Now the force of our Saviour's Argument from this Prediction, lies in this: If God hath promiſed to reveal to Men the knowledge of ſaving Truth, and to convince them that he doth reveal it; then no Man to whom this Revelation is made, ſhall want ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient means of Inſtruction and Conviction: and conſequently, every Man that is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of worldly Luſts and Intereſts, will be effectually wrought upon by them. And this freedom from ſuch Prejudices our Lord here calls <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>learning</hi> of the Father, which is the ſame with being <hi>given</hi> or <hi>drawn to Chriſt,</hi> (the Phraſe uſed before;) and this intimates, that it is ſomething we do towards the preparing our ſelves; and that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40809:32"/> we may alſo hinder it: For Hearing and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are voluntary Actions. A Man may ſtop his Ears againſt Inſtruction, and alienate his Mind from what is ſuggeſted to him: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomething Men may do to attain that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Heart which the Divine Inſpiration work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: They may alſo quench this Work of the Holy Spirit. The meaning of the whole is, as if our Lord had ſaid, You muſt have God for your Maſter, before you can be the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Son: You muſt be prepared by thoſe qualities, which there is no need of a new Revelation to teach you, before you are fit to receive that Doctrine which the Son brings. And now it is plain, that theſe very Speeches and Reaſonings of our Saviour, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to prepare them for Conviction and Faith: For by ſhewing them the great need of a teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Spirit in hearing and learning of God, and what Bleſſings the want of this Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would bereave them of, and by repeating and inculcating upon them, that great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of the Reſurrection at the laſt Day; he did what was moſt proper in it ſelf to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to a better Mind, to weaken their Prejudices, and to make them attend to thoſe Teſtimonies of his coming from God, which they had already ſeen, inſtead of deſiring more Signs, which in the temper they were in at preſent, would have done them no good if they had been granted.</p>
                  <p n="46">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40809:32"/>46. The meaning of which Scriptures is not, that any Man ſhall be immediately taught by the Father: For the Will of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not thus to be manifeſted to any of you, it being the Priviledge of the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, intimately to know his Mind, without the mediation of any other Perſon, [<hi>Ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 18.]</p>
                  <p n="47">47. Take notice therefore of what I ſay, The Will of my Father, which by me he makes known to you, is this, that he who receiveth my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, firmly believing it, and ſubmitting his Heart and Soul to it, ſhall as ſurely obtain Everlaſting Life, as if he were poſſeſs'd of it already.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 47. This Saying of our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains all that he ſays about the neceſſity of <hi>eating,</hi> &amp;c. ſhewing clearly, that he meant the believing of his Doctrine, and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to it in Heart and Life. For if he that <hi>believeth</hi> ſhall obtain everlaſting Life, then he <hi>eateth Chriſt,</hi> according to his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Chapter, that believeth in him.</p>
                  <p n="48">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40809:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>48. And therefore, as I told you before, you are to look upon me as the <hi>True Bread of Life,</hi> whereof I have been ſpeaking to you; for I came down from Heaven to guide you to everlaſting Life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 48. Here our Lord calleth himſelf <hi>Bread</hi> again, thereby implying what he afterwards expreſſed, that he is to be <hi>eaten.</hi> Now moſt certainly we are in ſuch a ſence to <hi>eat</hi> Chriſt, as that is wherein he is Bread. But no Man will ſay, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> was, or can be properly <hi>Bread;</hi> therefore it is not eating him literally and properly that can be here meant, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believing on him, which is by the ſame Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure called <hi>eating,</hi> whereby he called himſelf <hi>Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="49">49. Which ſhould make you concerned to attend my Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, inſtead of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring ſuch Bread as <hi>Moſes</hi> gave your Fathers in the Wilderneſs, which ſerved only to ſuſtain a ſhort Life in this World, for they are long ſince dead that ate it, [<hi>v.</hi> 31, 34.]</p>
                  <p n="50">50. But I bring you Food from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which whoſoever eateth, it ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40809:33"/> him to everlaſting Life: For I bring you a Doctrine, the Belief and Obedience whereof will avail to your Salvation; and I who bring it, am come with the higheſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to require your Faith, and with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Teſtimonies of my Authority to juſtifie your Faith; ſo that nothing is wanting to ſecure your Salvation, but forwardneſs on your own parts to eat this Heavenly Food that I invite you to feaſt upon, now that it is brought down to you from Heaven, and is as near you, as that Bread wherewith I fed you yeſterday in the Wilderneſs. Nothing is wanting, I ſay, but that you would think who it is that God hath ſent to you, and of how great concern to your Souls that Meſſage is which I bring you from Heaven, and how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly God hath teſtified that I am come from him to give you everlaſting Life: and that conſidering theſe things, you would do like reaſonable Men, believe what I ſay, and receive my Doctrine into your very Hearts and Souls, and give thanks to God for his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Gift.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 50. This is the firſt place where our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, in purſuance of that Figure of calling himſelf <hi>Bread,</hi> expreſſeth <hi>believing</hi> in him, [<hi>v.</hi> 35, 47.] by <hi>eating</hi> him. In the 35th <hi>ver.</hi> where he alſo calls himſelf the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> he did not purſue the Figure throughout, by ſaying, <hi>he that eateth me,</hi> but <hi>he that cometh to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40809:34"/> me, i. e.</hi> who is my Diſciple, <hi>ſhall never hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> and, <hi>he that believeth on me,</hi> (not <hi>he that drinketh me) ſhall never thirſt:</hi> Which makes it very plain, that by <hi>eating</hi> here we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>believing;</hi> not a corporeal, but a ſpiritual Action. And becauſe it does not yet appear that he limits the Object of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, we are therefore to underſtand him as ſpeaking of the neceſſity of receiving his whole Doctrine, and ſubmitting to it in Heart and Life; which whoſoever does, ſhall not die, but live eternally.</p>
                  <p n="51">51. And when I tell you, that <hi>I am the living Bread which came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and <hi>which he that eateth of, ſhall live for ever;</hi> as you are to underſtand this with reſpect to all that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which I deliver, ſo eſpecially with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that part of it, that <hi>I am come</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, to lay down my Life for the Salvation of Mankind. And as I came for this end, ſo I <hi>will give</hi> my Body to the Death, for the Life of the World; which is an infinitely greater Benefit, than either your Fathers received from <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40809:34"/> gave them <hi>Manna</hi> to eat; or than you received from me yeſterday, when you were filled with that Proviſion I made for your Bodies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 51. Without doing great Violence to our Saviour's Words in this place, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo underſtood, as if he promiſed to turn Bread into his Fleſh, for the Life of the World; as they muſt ſuppoſe, who will ground the Roman Doctrine of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation upon this place. For if ſome ſuch Change were here to be underſtood, it muſt be quite contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> a Change of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> into <hi>Bread;</hi> inaſmuch as he calls himſelf <hi>the living Bread,</hi> and ſays, That <hi>the Bread which he would give was his Fleſh, that he would give for the Life of the World.</hi> If therefore it be inſiſted upon, that the Words are to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly underſtood; and that therefore a change muſt be ſuppoſed, of one Subſtance into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, it muſt not be of <hi>Bread</hi> into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Chriſt's Fleſh,</hi> but of <hi>Chriſt's Fleſh</hi> into the ſubſtance of <hi>Bread;</hi> which Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I think no body has ever yet been ſo unreaſonable as to contend for. What account therefore is to be given of theſe Words, but this, That our Saviour having hitherto pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued a Figurative way of ſpeaking, upon the occaſion ſo often mentioned, went on in the ſame way of expreſſion, to lay before them that principal Doctrine of the Goſpel, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to die for the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40809:35"/> which is the plain ſence of <hi>giving his Fleſh to be bread for us:</hi> For he <hi>gave his Fleſh for the Life of the World,</hi> when he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Death for us all: And his <hi>Fleſh ſo given,</hi> is <hi>Bread</hi> to us, becauſe his <hi>Death</hi> is the means of our <hi>living</hi> for ever.</p>
                  <p>And whereas <hi>Chriſt</hi> mentioned the giving of his <hi>Fleſh for the Life of the World,</hi> as a future thing; and likewiſe the <hi>giving of his Fleſh to be Bread;</hi> it does not follow, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the former was to be performed on the Croſs only, therefore the latter was to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed only in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> This, I ſay, does not follow, unleſs it could be proved that he promiſed, in thoſe Words, to give us his natural Fleſh to be eaten properly in the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt;</hi> which I have ſhewn is impoſſible to be proved from hence. Still therefore we are to underſtand, not a <hi>corporal,</hi> but a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> eating: And whereas our Saviour ſaid, The Bread which <hi>I will</hi> give is my Fleſh, which <hi>I will</hi> give for the Life of the World; the meaning is this, that his Fleſh ſhall be given for the Life of the World, <hi>once for all;</hi> but the Spiritual Food or Nouriſhment, which his Fleſh ſo given, ſhould afford, would be <hi>given ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> not only in the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> but in the whole miniſtration of the Goſpel; which holds forth the Death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and offers the bleſſed Fruits and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages thereof to all that are diſpoſed to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of them.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40809:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>It is alſo objected againſt this Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That if the Doctrine of our Lord's Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the believing of it, be here meant, no reaſon can be given, why our Saviour ſhould ſpeak in the Future Tenſe, The Bread which <hi>I will give</hi> is my Fleſh: Since this Spiritual Food was no leſs given before the Incarnation and Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; for the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> lived and were nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by Faith. And therefore if ſpiritual eating be only intended, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſeemed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a new thing, which yet he had given of old: So that his Promiſe is to be underſtood, of giving his natural Fleſh to be eaten, which was never done before the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> This is the Objection; and a very ſtrange one it muſt needs be to him that ſhall conſider, 1. That our Saviour ſpeaketh in the Future Tenſe to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> where yet the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is acknowledged to be Figurative, and the meaning of it to be <hi>believing: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever drinketh of the Water that I ſhall give him, ſhall never thirſt; but the Water that I ſhall give him,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>ſhall be in him a Well, &amp;c.</hi> Now would not this be rare arguing, Our Lord ſays, <hi>I will give</hi> Water: Therefore he promiſed ſomething that he had never giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en before; therefore ſpiritual drinking, or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,</hi> is not meant, becauſe the Patriarchs <hi>believed</hi> of old, therefore the Promiſe is to be taken literally and properly? And yet this is that very Argument to prove the literal ſence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40809:36"/> in this Verſe. But then, 2. Our Lord ſpeaks of the neceſſity of preſent eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood, in the 53d and 54th Verſes. And therefore the Argument from the Future Tenſe, to prove that he ſpake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> is inſufficient. 3. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that all had been future, and that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was promiſed more than had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly given, yet it follows not that <hi>Christ</hi> ſpake properly of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> much leſs of giving his Fleſh properly to be eaten there. For although the Fathers believed of old, yet the Doctrine of the Paſſion was never clearly underſtood by the Faithful before our Saviour's Time; no, nor as yet by his own Diſciples. Our Saviour did now and then mention it; and here he gave them ſome Intimations, of it, which they underſtood not then ſo well as they did afterwards. [See Note on <hi>V.</hi> 53.] Himſelf ſaid to them, <hi>Many Prophets and righteous Men have deſired to ſee thoſe things that ye have ſeen, and have not ſeen them; and to hear thoſe things that ye hear, and have not heard them,</hi> Matth. 13.17. And yet his Diſciples hitherto had attained to a very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect knowledge of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to what they had afterwards. Although therefore the good Men of old were juſtified by Faith, and ſaw the Promiſes afar off, and had ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Intimations of the Goſpel; yet whether the particular Objects of our Faith were not a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40809:36"/> 
                     <hi>new</hi> thing worthy of <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Promiſe, I leave indifferent Men to judge.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, It has been ſaid, That the Natural Fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to be <hi>given,</hi> or offered up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs ſubſtantially or properly <hi>for the Life of the World,</hi> and therefore the ſame Fleſh was to be given with the ſame Propriety, to be <hi>Bread</hi> for us, and to be eaten by us, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> To which I anſwer, 1. as before, That this arguing will conclude more than they deſire who urge it. For if the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Clauſe is to be underſtood in the ſame ſtrictneſs and propriety of words with the latter Clauſe, then the <hi>Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt was to become <hi>Bread</hi> properly. For he ſaid, <hi>The Bread which I will give, is my Fleſh.</hi> But, 2. It is much more reaſonable to underſtand the <hi>giving of his Fleſh to be Bread,</hi> according to the meaning of this kind of Expreſſions throughout the whole Diſcourſe: And our Adverſaries do acknowledge, that thoſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, <hi>I am the Bread of Life; He that eateth of this Bread, ſhall live for ever;</hi> that is, all of this kind from <hi>Verſ.</hi> 32. to this very Clauſe in <hi>Verſ.</hi> 51. are to be underſtood of ſpiritual eating, <hi>i. e.</hi> of believing. Since therefore our Saviour gave no manner of intimation that he changed his ſtyle, there is more reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret thoſe words, of <hi>giving his Fleſh to be Bread,</hi> and of <hi>eating</hi> his Fleſh, and <hi>drinking</hi> his Blood, in a ſence agreeable to that, wherein <hi>eating Him</hi> is to be underſtood all along be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40809:37"/> than to underſtand them properly, that is to ſay, of <hi>bodily eating;</hi> although it is the Fleſh of Chriſt which is given to be eaten, that Fleſh which was ſubſtantially and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given for the <hi>Life of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="52">52. Upon this the <hi>Jews</hi> diſputed againſt him afreſh, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of them ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his laſt words in a groſs ſence, as if he had promiſed to give them his Fleſh to eat with their Teeth, and to ſwallow it down their Throats, as their Forefathers had eaten <hi>Manna,</hi> and as they had eaten in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the day before. And upon this advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which they thought they had againſt him, they exclaimed as if he had ſpoken ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly and inhumanly, and taught his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to devour Man's Fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="53">53. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this perverſe Conſtruction of his words, <hi>Jeſus</hi> did not think fit to deliver his meaning in ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Expreſſions as might avoid all the Cavils of theſe unreaſonable Men, but defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for a while a further Explication of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he vehemently repeated his Doctrine, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch Expreſſions and figurative Speeches,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40809:37"/> as they had hitherto given him juſt occaſion to uſe; only to ſignifie that he was to die a violent and bloody Death for the Salvation of Mankind: To that Expreſſion of <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> he added another, of <hi>drinking his Blood;</hi> affirming, that except they did this, they muſt not expect Eternal Life; as if he had ſaid, <q>Except ye believe the Merit of that Sacrifice which I ſhall offer for the Sins of the World, and own me for your Saviour, in dying a painful and ignominious Death for your ſakes, and learn Charity, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Humility, and Reſignation to the Will of God, by my Sufferings, ye have not Spiritual, nor ſhall have Eternal Life.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 53. If it be asked, Why our Saviour ſtill perſiſted in a figurative and alluſive way of Expreſſion, although he ſaw their groſs, and perhaps wilful miſtake of his former words? [<hi>v.</hi> 52.] It may be anſwered, That he knew good reaſon for it, though the Reaſon be not left upon Record. However, a probable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture ought to ſuffice in ſuch a Caſe as this, where the Objection is, That no account can be given of it. I anſwer therefore, That our Lord did not think fit to foretel the ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Death he was to ſuffer upon the Croſs, ſo publickly as he foretold his Reſurrection. Sometimes he told his Diſciples that he was <hi>to ſuffer,</hi> and <hi>be killed, [Matth.</hi> 16.] but to others he intimated it obſcurely, with intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40809:38"/> that they might afterwards remember what he ſaid, rather than that they ſhould underſtand it preſently. But neither to the Multitude, nor to his Diſciples, did he clearly ſignifie the <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Ends</hi> of his Paſſion; this ſeeming to be one of thoſe things that they <hi>could not bear now,</hi> but which the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter ſhould reveal to them afterward. It may therefore be ſaid, That our Lord did not deliver the Doctrine concerning the Death he was to ſuffer, and the bleſſed Fruits thereof to all Believers, in ſuch-like plain words and expreſſions, as I have endeavoured to uſe in the Paraphraſe, becauſe he uſed to conceal the former from the People, and reſerve the clear manifeſtation of the latter, till after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſion, when theſe Sayings would be <hi>brought to remembrance,</hi> and better underſtood than they were at firſt. But one may ask, Why did he not at leaſt tell theſe Men, that theſe were <hi>ſtill</hi> but Expreſſions of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> things, by way of <hi>alluſion</hi> to things <hi>ſenſible?</hi> To which I anſwer, That he did thus explain himſelf to his Diſciples preſently after, and that upon occaſion of this groſs Miſtake, [ſee <hi>V.</hi> 62, 63.] and nothing appears to the contrary, but that this Explication was made in the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> in the Hearing of all. But whether it was ſo or not, 'tis ſufficient for us that he explained himſelf as he did to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40809:38"/>
                  <p>In the mean time, Cardinal <hi>Cajetan</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this place cannot be underſtood of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> becauſe then it would infer a neceſſity of the Peoples receiving the <hi>Cup,</hi> is an Argument <hi>ad Homines,</hi> plain and ſtrong. Neither is it to be avoided, by pretending that <hi>Chriſt</hi> does not ſpeak of the <hi>Species</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Bread or Wine, but of the <hi>Things</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under them; and therefore that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>whole Chriſt</hi> is contained under <hi>one kind,</hi> the Condition of Eternal Life is fulfilled, by receiving him under <hi>either kind:</hi> For they that receive him under the <hi>Species</hi> of a Wafer, or a morſel of Bread only, which is to be eaten, cannot with any Modeſty be ſaid to <hi>drink</hi> his Blood; which is yet made as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary as <hi>eating</hi> his Fleſh. We grant, that <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> being taken as figurative Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, do ſignifie the ſame thing, <hi>viz. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving;</hi> and we ſay, that <hi>believing,</hi> when 'tis expreſſed by <hi>eating</hi> his Fleſh, and <hi>drinking</hi> his Blood, refers to that particular Object of Faith, the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſignified by the ſeparate mention of his <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> But <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking</hi> being taken properly, do not ſignify the ſame thing. If therefore our Saviour is to be underſtood properly, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him in the <hi>Eucharist</hi> by eating his Fleſh and drinking his Blood: The words are plain, beyond all diſpute, that he is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by <hi>drinking his Blood</hi> there, as well as by <hi>eating his Fleſh:</hi> Which ſince the Church
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40809:39"/> of <hi>Rome</hi> denies to the Laity, the Cardinal had good reaſon not to underſtand theſe words of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> being concerned, as he was, to make the beſt of all thoſe Uſages which he found in his Church. And yet I doubt this great Man hath not quite delivered that Church from all the Reproof this very Text has for their half Communion. For although theſe words are not to be underſtood properly of the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> yet, I think, what <hi>Grotius</hi> ſays, cannot be reaſonably denied, <hi>viz.</hi> that here is a <hi>Tacit Alluſion to the Euchariſt.</hi> And if that be true, the Text even thus taken, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn their witholding the Cup from the Laity. For the Alluſion muſt conſiſt in this, that, as according to the Inſtitution of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> the Holy Bread and Cup were <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately</hi> taken to ſhew forth the violent Death of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> ſo in theſe words of <hi>eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood,</hi> the believing of his meritorious Death, and following the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his Patience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is expreſſed by the <hi>ſeparate</hi> mention of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> and therefore of <hi>eating</hi> the one, and <hi>drinking</hi> the other. Which alluſion is ſo apt, that I ſhould not wonder, if it inclines thoſe that enquire no further, to believe that our Saviour here ſpeaks of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> But ſince the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate taking of the Holy Bread and the Holy Cup in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> on the one ſide, and the ſeparate mention of his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> on the other, is that in which the Alluſion conſiſts,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40809:39"/> it is utterly deſtroyed by the pretended <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitance, i. e.</hi> by giving the Body and Blood, not as ſeparated, but as united; or by giving the Body and Blood to be eaten; not the Fleſh to be eaten, and the Blood to be drunk. In ſhort, as our Saviour did Sacramentally repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Death, by taking the Holy Bread, and the Holy Cup, ſeparately, and giving them ſeparately; ſo he did in Words, alluding to that Sacrament, repreſent the ſame Death, <hi>i. e.</hi> by the diſtinct mention of his Fleſh and Blood; and he repreſented alſo the neceſſity of Faith in his Death, under the diſtinct Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood. And therefore they who in the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi> pretend to give both Kinds in one, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the reaſon why theſe words allude to the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> But if they ſay, that our Saviour here ſpeaks properly of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> nothing can be more evident, than that they openly condemn themſelves, in denying that to the People, which, as they ſay, he required in <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> and expreſs Terms; and that is, the <hi>drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in truth, they deſtroy the ſignificancy of the Sacrament, which is no otherwiſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of our Lord's Death, than as it repreſents the ſeparation of his Fleſh and Blood. And then I deſire them to tell me, how they can be ſaid to commemorate the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by receiving a Sacrament that ſhews forth the ſeparation of his Body and Blood,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40809:40"/> who do not receive them ſeparated, but uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? St. <hi>Paul</hi> concluding the End of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Inſtitution of it, ſaid, <hi>As often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lord's Death till he come:</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof is exceeding plain, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe the ſeparation of the Blood from the Body is <hi>ſhewn,</hi> by the diſtinct taking of the Bread and the Cup, to eat the one, and drink the other. But this Reaſon is ſo confounded by the <hi>Half-Communion,</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>Concomitance,</hi> that the Inſtitution is not only contradicted, but, I fear, the Sacrament is denied to them that receive one Kind only; and that they have not ſo much as an <hi>Half-Communion,</hi> inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they do not receive a Sacrament that ſhews the Death of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="54">54. <q>But he that is ſo far from rejecting me, and being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at me, becauſe of that painful Death which I am to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that he doth, on the other hand, receive all that Divine Inſtruction which it does af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and turns it into ſpiritual Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by learning the high diſpleaſure of God againſt Sin, and his infinite Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and the Vanity of this World, and the worth of his own Soul, and the neceſſity of Repentance, and of a Godly Life; my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40809:40"/> Death ſhall be to him a means of that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life, to which I ſhall raiſe him at the laſt day; and this as certainly, as if he were now in <hi>actual poſſeſſion of it.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 54. Becauſe our Lord continues in his Speech, to make a ſeparate mention of his Fleſh and Blood; it follows, that he ſtill ſpeaks of his Death, and the particular Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Death, which would be entertained with the greateſt difficulty, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>he was a Sacrifice for the Sins of the World;</hi> and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Saviour, becauſe crucified, &amp;c.</hi> The live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belief whereof is, that which our Lord means by <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood;</hi> and not eating and drinking the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> of his Body and Blood, which a Man may do to his Condemnation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſometimes under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood theſe words of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> yet he did not ſo underſtand them, as if every one who partakes of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> does alſo <hi>Eat the Fleſh, and Drink the Blood of Chriſt;</hi> for he manifeſtly denied that the Wicked were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the very Body of Chriſt, though they partook of the Sacrament of his Body: And yet 'tis impoſſible but they muſt do the one as well as the other, if it be true, that the proper Subſtance of the Body of Chriſt is in the Sacrament, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends. And by conſequence, if this corporal <hi>eating</hi> be intended, it ſeems clearly to follow,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40809:41"/> that no Man who partakes of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> can be damned; which is certainly very falſe, and therefore <hi>corporal eating</hi> cannot be meant here, but only <hi>ſpiritual eating.</hi> And ſo St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> underſtood it, although he applied theſe Words ſometimes to the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as he denied that the Wicked do eat the Fleſh, and drink the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though with their Mouths they take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his Body and Blood. But becauſe this ſpiritual eating, which is neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, is by no means confined to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of the Euchariſt; and becauſe many do not partake ſpiritually in the Body and Blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> that yet do partake of the Sacrament, I cannot underſtand why our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhould ſpeak here directly and properly of the Euchariſt; and therefore I adhere to the ſence of thoſe Fathers who interpret this place, and thoſe that follow, of ſpiritual Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons only.</p>
                  <p n="55">55. <q>So that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> concerning my <hi>Sufferings</hi> and <hi>Death,</hi> which will give the greateſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to Unbelievers, is the <hi>moſt excellent Meat</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> becauſe it is the <hi>Food of Souls,</hi> when 'tis received with a firm and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious <hi>Faith;</hi> and will ſecure alſo the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body to everlaſting Life.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:40809:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 55.</hi> He continues to diſtinguiſh the <hi>Fleſh</hi> from the <hi>Blood,</hi> and therefore ſtill ſpeaks of his Paſſion, giving ſome kind of preeminence to Faith in his Death, above the belief of other particular Doctrines, though that would be admitted with greateſt difficulty.</p>
                  <p n="56">56. <q>And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth my <hi>Death</hi> to be a Sacrifice for the Sins of the World, and does thereby learn that Duty which it teacheth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Comfort which it affordeth, he will love me, and devote himſelf entirely to my Service, becauſe I have thus humbled my ſelf; though that be the reaſon for which ſuch as you will be violently prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt me. And on the other ſide, he ſhall be peculiarly beloved and cared for by me: For though in love to Mankind I am to be made an Offering for Sin, yet 'tis a particular care I ſhall expreſs towards thoſe, who have a true ſenſe of my Sufferings in their behalf, who make a right uſe of them, and return that thankfulneſs and obedience which their Faith requires, [1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10.]</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 56.</hi> His purſuance of the ſame Expreſſion, ſtill ſhews that he ſpeaks of the ſame thing,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40809:42"/> 
                     <hi>viz.</hi> believing his death to be a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> &amp;c. And here he intimates, that his Sufferings, which would be a Stumbling block to Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, would be an effectual Engagement to all good Men to love him; and that their fervent Love, and humble Gratitude, would be rewarded with his eſpecial Love. For as God's <hi>dwelling in Men,</hi> ſignifies his gracious Preſence amongſt them, and his delight in doing them good; ſo their <hi>dwelling in him,</hi> ſignifies their Love to him, and conſtant attendance upon the doing of his Will, and the delight they have in knowing themſelves to be always in his Preſence.</p>
                  <p n="57">57. <q>And one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Expreſſion (and that of weight enough to make you conſider what I ſay) of my peculiar love to every ſuch Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, is what I have told you already; and I do earneſtly repeat it again: As ſure as the Father who ſent me will raiſe me from the Dead, ſo ſurely will I raiſe up every one to everlaſting Life, that believeth my Doctrine, and liveth by his Faith.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. 57.</hi> Here our Lord ſeems to leave the ſpecial conſideration of his Sufferings and Death, and to ſpeak now of his whole Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40809:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> as he had done before; for as by eating his <hi>Fleſh</hi> and drinking his <hi>Blood,</hi> we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand believing the merit and inſtruction of his <hi>Death,</hi> &amp;c. ſo by eating <hi>Him,</hi> we are taught before [<hi>V.</hi> 35, 47, 50.] to underſtand believing him in general, that is, believing all his Doctrine.</p>
                  <p n="58">58. <q>Mark there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what I ſay to you [<hi>V.</hi> 33, 35.] at firſt, That I am that true Bread from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, wherewith the <hi>Manna</hi> that your Fathers ate, and the Bread which you ate yeſterday, are not to be compared; for they were good for nothing but to preſerve a mortal Life for a ſhort time; whereas he that feedeth upon the Word and Doctrine which God hath ſent you from <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſhall be raiſed from the Dead, to aſcend thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to live there for ever.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 58. Here he concludes all, with return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſame thing, and uſing the very Expreſſions that he began withal, [<hi>V.</hi> 32, 35.50.] than which we need not a clearer proof, that he all along ſpake in the ſame ſtyle, and in thoſe Expreſſions of <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> perpetually alluded to the <hi>Manna</hi> and the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40809:43"/> 
                     <hi>Loaves</hi> in the Wilderneſs; which gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to all this Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p n="59">59. Theſe things he ſaid publickly in the Synagogue at <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaum,</hi> where the People, whom he had fed in the Wilderneſs, found him, [<hi>V.</hi> 24, 25.] and gave him the occaſion of diſcourſing in this manner, by following him for the <hi>Loaves,</hi> [<hi>V.</hi> 26.] and (when they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſappointed) by ſetting the <hi>Manna</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> gave their Fathers, againſt the feeding ſo many thouſands the day before, [<hi>V.</hi> 31.] And the great end of his Diſcourſe upon this occaſion, was to draw their Minds from world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to heavenly Things, and to make them more deſirous of the Spiritual and Heavenly Benefits of his Miracles, than of the bodily relief which they had found by them.</p>
                  <p n="60">60. But becauſe he expreſſed his Mind in this figurative way, and was by many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as if he had commended to them the eating of his <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and drinking of his Blood, in the literal ſence; therefore many, even of thoſe that had for ſome time followed him, talked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, as if theſe Sayings of their Maſter, muſt needs be offenſive to the Ears
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40809:43"/> of all Perſons that had a ſence of Humanity; and as for themſelves, that they knew not what to make of them.</p>
                  <p n="61">61. Neither did they deſire him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain himſelf further; but he, by his Divine Spirit, knowing what they muttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, applied himſelf to them in particular, and upbraided them in this manner for taking ſo unreaſonable an offence againſt him.</p>
                  <p n="62">62. <q>When you ſhall ſee me <hi>aſcend up to Heaven,</hi> it will not ſeem ſtrange that <hi>I came down from thence;</hi> and becauſe even then it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main neceſſary that you ſhould <hi>eat my Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drink my Blood;</hi> you may be ſure, I do not mean, that groſs feeding upon my Fleſh, and drinking my Blood, in which you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what I have ſaid; for my Body will then be too far removed from the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mortal Men, to be capable of being ſo uſed.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="63">63. <q>No; when I ſpeak to you of the Conditions of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining everlaſting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40809:44"/> Life, though I have now expreſſed them, by <hi>eating my Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking my Blood;</hi> yet you had reaſon to underſtand me of ſpiritual Actions, which do indeed tend to the bettering of the inward Man. For they are ſuch things only that feed the Soul, and can preſerve it to Eternal Life: But to this purpoſe <hi>the fleſh profiteth nothing;</hi> No, not my <hi>own Fleſh,</hi> if you ſhould eat it as groſly as you underſtand my Sayings: For even this would be but bodily Nouriſhment, but would have no Influence upon the Mind. But if you would know what thoſe things are that better the Soul, (and it is my Buſineſs to call you off from that ſollicitous Care you take of your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bodies, to mind your Souls, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for a bleſſed Reſurrection:) If, I ſay, you would know what things are proper for the Improvement of the Mind, they are the <hi>Words that I ſpeak unto you;</hi> they are thoſe Precepts of a heavenly Life, and thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of eternal Life which I have laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you; that Faith which I require you to have in my Death, and that Example of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Charity and Humility, which I require you to follow. Theſe are the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> means of renewing your Minds, and therefore Means alſo of fitting you for Eternal Life.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40809:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 61, 62, 63. Our Lord perceiving how groſly the Jews, and ſome of his own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, underſtood thoſe Expreſſions, of eating his Fleſh, and drinking his Blood, did upon this occaſion explain his own meaning as fully as he did to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in the point of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. For <hi>Nicodemus</hi> having ſaid, <hi>How can a Man be born when he is old? Can he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſecond time into his Mothers Womb and be born? Jeſus anſwered, Verily verily, I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, except a Man be born of Water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God. That which is born of the Fleſh, is Fleſh; and that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit.</hi> Which was as much as to ſay, <hi>The Fleſh profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing,</hi> (as here, <hi>V.</hi> 63.) <q>And if you were, by a ſtrange Miracle, to be born again the natural way, by this <hi>fleſhly</hi> Birth, you would come again but into a mortal Life; but that fleſhly Birth would not avail you for everlaſting Life.</q> In the very ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner our Saviour repeated, in this Chapter, thoſe Sayings which the Jews and ſome of his own Diſciples were offended at; and in the ſame manner he explained them afterwards. <hi>It is the Spirit that quickneth; the Fleſh profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing: the words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are Life.</hi> Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared with the Anſwer to <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> now mentioned and explained, by the light that Anſwer affords, can yield no other mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40809:45"/> than that which I have expreſſed in the Paraphraſe.</p>
                  <p>As for the 62d <hi>V.</hi> it might be intended as an Anſwer to that particular Exception againſt him, mentioned <hi>V.</hi> 42. that he was the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and could not therefore reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pretend to come down from Heaven: To which if our Lord referred, his words are a proper Anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> that when they ſhould ſee him aſcend into Heaven, they would no longer doubt of the truth of his coming from thence. But I rather think thoſe words refer to that great Offence which ſome of his own Diſciples took againſt him, that he ſhould ſpeak of their <hi>eating of his Fleſh, and drinking of his Blood:</hi> For they were his Diſciples on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſaw him aſcend. And when they ſhould know that he was in Heaven, they could not, without great Stupidity, think that he would give them his Fleſh to eat, and his Blood to drink, in that groſs ſence wherein they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood him. However, I have put both theſe Interpretations into the Paraphraſe.</p>
                  <p n="64">64. <q>But no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that you wreſt my Sayings to ſo abſurd a ſence as you do; for there are ſome amongſt you that diſlike my Doctrine, and are grown weary of following me, and wait
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40809:45"/> for an opportunity to leave me.</q> For as ſoon as any Man profeſſed himſelf his Diſciple, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> knew how he ſtood affected towards him. And he did not only know who of the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude that follow'd him would revolt, but likewiſe which of his Apoſtles would betray him. See <hi>V.</hi> 36.</p>
                  <p n="65">65. And <hi>Jeſus</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <q>Becauſe I knew that there were ſome ſuch amongſt you, therefore I thought fit to tell you before, [<hi>V.</hi> 37, 39, 44.] that my Doctrine would never be heartily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, by any but thoſe whom God had prepared for it, by enduing them with a Mind willing to learn, and with a prevailing deſire of obtaining God's Favour, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="66">66. Upon this cloſe application of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of thoſe inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Diſciples of his; they finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſcovered, and that it was to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſſemble, reſolved to pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves his Diſciples no longer, and went off from him without more ado.</p>
                  <p n="67">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:40809:46"/>67. <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſeeing them turn their Backs upon him, took this occaſion both to ſhew that ſome of his Diſciples were ſincere, and that he cared not to be followed by any but thoſe that were willing; and therefore he ſaid to the Twelve, You ſee I do not compel Men to follow me, but that I let them depart if they will go. Now what ſay you? will ye ſtill continue my Diſciples, or follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of theſe Men, and go away?</p>
                  <p n="68">68. Whereupon <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (who was ſtill the moſt forward Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his Maſter's Cauſe) anſwered for himſelf and the reſt; Lord, our greateſt concern is, to attain <hi>eternal Life;</hi> and there is none other but thy ſelf who can guide us to it. And we underſtand, that thoſe very Sayings of thine, with which theſe Men were ſo unreaſonably offended, do ſhew us the neceſſity of believing <hi>thy Words</hi> and Doctrine (as thou didſt now tell them) [<hi>V.</hi> 63.] that we may live for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 68. <hi>Thou haſt the words of eternal Life.</hi> This ſaying of St. <hi>Peter</hi> confirms the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation I have given of <hi>V.</hi> 63. For here he ſeems plainly to repeat our Lord's ſence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the ſame Words; <hi>The Words that I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40809:46"/> ſpeak unto you, they are Life;</hi> or, <hi>the Words of Eternal Life:</hi> As if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had ſaid, We do not underſtand thee in that groſs and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Senſe to which theſe Men have perverted thy Sayings; for we perceive that thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of thoſe Doctrines and Revelations by which we are to be guided to eternal Life. But if St. <hi>Peter</hi> had underſtood our Saviour in that ſence wherein the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and his revolted Diſciples underſtood him, St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Anſwer would ſurely have been to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Whatever appearance there is of Inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Contradiction in giving thy</hi> Fleſh to be eaten, and thy Blood to be drunk, <hi>for the Life of the World; yet we believe that we ſhall eat thy natural Fleſh, and drink,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe thou hast ſaid it: For though this hard Saying ſtaggered thoſe Men that are gone off, yet it does not ſtagger us at all.</hi> This had been a Confeſſion of Faith ſuitable to the occaſion, and to the Spirit of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> if he had underſtood our Saviour as the <hi>Jews</hi> did. At leaſt he would have uſed thoſe very Expreſſions which our Saviour uſed when the <hi>Jews</hi> took offence, <hi>i. e.</hi> he would have ſaid, <hi>To whom ſhould we go but to thee, who wilt give us thy Fleſh to eat, and thy Blood to drink, that we may have Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life?</hi> But when he rather choſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his Faith in the Explanatory words, <hi>V.</hi> 63. <hi>Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi> I think a reaſonable Man muſt acknowledge that St. <hi>Peter</hi> did not underſtand our Saviour's
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40809:47"/> Expreſſions, as the perverſe <hi>Jews</hi> underſtood them.</p>
                  <p n="69">69. And we have already arrived to this <hi>Faith,</hi> by ſeeing thy mighty Works, and hearing thy Divine Doctrines; for by theſe Teſtimonies we are convinced, beyond all doubt, that thou art the promiſed <hi>Meſſias;</hi> and whereas theſe Men caſted thee the Son of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> we aſſuredly believe that thou art the <hi>Son</hi> of that <hi>God</hi> who giveth Life to All, and will give Eternal Life to all that believe in thee. And to this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>Peter</hi>'s all the reſt aſſented.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V.</hi> 69. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> having thus ſhewed plainly enough, what he underſtood by the Fleſh and Blood of <hi>Jeſus, viz.</hi> his Doctrine, or <hi>words of eternal Life;</hi> he ſhews as plainly in this Verſe, what he and the reſt underſtood by <hi>eating, viz. believing,</hi> as <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf had explained it before, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 47. Therefore, ſays he, <hi>And we believe, and are ſure,</hi> &amp;c. So that by what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, it appears ſufficiently, that if <hi>Jeſus</hi> had meant the literal and groſs ſence, the <hi>Jews</hi> and the Diſciples that forſook him, underſtood him aright; and <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles and Diſciples that ſtaid, miſtook him; which 'tis certain they did not, becauſe our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40809:47"/> Saviour approved what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid in the name of all the reſt. And in the Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour's words, it is, I believe, more ſafe to follow St. <hi>Peter,</hi> with the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of our Saviour, than to follow any of his Succeſſors without it.</p>
                  <p n="70">70. But this being ſpoken in the Name of All: <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to ſhew that he as well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Hearts of his Twelve Apoſtles, as he did of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Diſciples, [<hi>V.</hi> 64.] anſwered them to this purpoſe; What one of you hath ſaid in behalf of All, is true of All but one. I have indeed choſen you Twelve before all my other Diſciples, to be my chief Companions and Miniſters; but there is one of you who already hates me, and is treacherouſly bent to do me miſchief.</p>
                  <p n="71">71. Though he did not mention <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytor, yet he meant him, and not any other of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:40809:48"/>
                  <head>THE CONCLUSION.</head>
                  <p>AND now I heartily beſeech All, into whoſe Hands theſe Papers may chance to come, not to think that this Chapter is to be done withal, when they are once ſatisfied what our Lords meaning was in thoſe Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Eating him,</hi> and the like; but that they would pleaſe to attend to the Reaſon and End of theſe, and ſuch kind of Sayings; which will convince them, I doubt not, that this excellent Chapter is fit to be thought of, and laid to heart every day they live.</p>
                  <p>Great pity it is, that this Portion of God's Word alſo, ſhould come to be a Bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention; which was deſigned to beget and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove in the Diſciples of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a Spirit of true Wiſdom and Piety, and to eſtabliſh them in a Holy Life.</p>
                  <p>That which our Lord principally aimed at in all this Diſcourſe, was, to make his Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers concerned in good earneſt for their Eternal State, which will at firſt ſight appear to any
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40809:48"/> Man that mindeth how often thoſe Sayings return, of <hi>everlaſting Life,</hi> and <hi>living for ever,</hi> and being <hi>raiſed up at the laſt day.</hi> Now this indeed ſeemed to be his great Deſign in almoſt all his Sermons and Applications to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; from whence we may gather this profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Inſtruction, that Men were more or leſs prepared to receive the Truth, as it is in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> according as they were more or leſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the End of his coming into the World, which was to bring them to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life.</p>
                  <p>But in this Chapter, and in ſome others, there is a peculiar Inſtruction tending to this purpoſe, which we ought all of us very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to conſider, not ſlighting it, becauſe it is very plain, but making much of it, both becauſe it is very uſeful, and ſtrongly ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Lord himſelf. And 'tis in ſhort this, that the <hi>Care</hi> we are at, and the Pains we take for the Welfare of this ſhort Life, ſhould awaken in us a greater care and concern for our everlaſting Welfare: And that we who are ſo thoughtful and diligent in purſuing our Temporal Intereſts, ſhould be aſhamed, and count our ſelves reproved by our worldly Cares, if we are not much more careful to <hi>work out our Salvation.</hi> This was the Method our Lord took to bring thoſe People to Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and therefore he repreſented to them the Means and Conditions of everlaſting Life, under the Names of thoſe Things which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40809:49"/> their Hearts had hitherto been moſt ſet upon, <hi>i.e. Bread,</hi> and <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking.</hi> For theſe were the Men that had been fed by him the day before; and now they followed him for the Loaves, that is, in hope to reap ſuch bodily Advantages as theſe from him every day. But to bring them to ſome ſenſe of better things, and to lead them towards a due Eſteem of that end for which he came into the World, he proceeds in his Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by calling the Spiritual Benefits which he had in ſtore for them, <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Food;</hi> and their receiving thoſe Benefits, <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking;</hi> ever and anon letting them know, that if they ate and drank of that Food, which he came to give them, they ſhould live for ever. And what was the Inſtruction of this way of diſcourſing to them, but that if the bodily Food, for which they were ſo ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous, were a valuable Enjoyment, which yet would ſerve but for the prolonging of a mortal Life, how ought they to hunger and thirſt for the Meat that would preſerve them for ever? And therefore when he came, in the ſame way of ſpeaking, to intimate to them thoſe Benefits of his Paſſion, which they would better underſtand afterwards than they could at preſent; He told them, <hi>My Fleſh is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed;</hi> as if he had told them in plainer Words than he thought fit to uſe at that time; <hi>It is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more profitable to enjoy the Fruits of my
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40809:49"/> Sufferings and Death, by being reconciled to God, by forbearing to provoke his Juſtice, and by following my Example, than if I ſhould take the ſame care of you as long as I live, which I did yeſterday, when I fed your Bodies by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this indeed ſeemed to be our Saviour's great Deſign in preaching the Neceſſity of Faith and Repentance, and a Godly Life to the People, under ſo many Figurative Expreſſions as we find he uſed, <hi>viz.</hi> to lead them by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Things, to the Care of Things Eternal, and to raiſe their Minds from Earth to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by a moſt familiar and convincing way of arguing with them, from Earthly Things themſelves. Therefore if he found them va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing themſelves upon their <hi>Liberty,</hi> or careful for <hi>Life,</hi> or labouring for <hi>Wealth,</hi> or ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous for <hi>Food:</hi> He called himſelf ſometimes, and ſometimes his Doctrine, and their receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, <hi>Liberty, Life,</hi> and <hi>Treaſure,</hi> and <hi>Meat,</hi> and <hi>Drink,</hi> as occaſion required; and this to let them underſtand, that there was a more real Good to be found in Faith and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, than in theſe, or any other kind of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Advantages; and that whatever reaſon they had to be concerned for theſe tranſitory Enjoyments, they had much more to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in receiving as they ought, thoſe Spiritual good Things which he came to confer upon them.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40809:50"/>
                  <p>If therefore we will ſuffer our ſelves to be inſtructed by ſuch Paſſages as theſe are; moſt of us, I fear, may learn, from our Concern about the things of this World, to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our remiſneſs in providing for a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And all of us ſhould learn to reflect ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often upon matters of greater Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when we are engaged even in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Deſigns of this Life, and purſuing the lawful Buſineſs thereof; and ſo we ſhould in ſome meaſure preach to our ſelves, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> once did to his Hearers when he was upon Earth.</p>
                  <p>And we ſhould not think that the <hi>Jews</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had need of this kind of Inſtruction, who I confeſs had been Educated under a <hi>Law,</hi> that promiſed little elſe beſides <hi>Temporal</hi> Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to thoſe that obſerved it: but that we our ſelves, who know the great Bleſſings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to be <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> ſtand in need alſo of ſuch Admonitions as theſe are: For the Cares of this World, and the Love of its Riches, and Pleaſures, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, are as apt to take hold of us, as they were of the <hi>Jews,</hi> if we do not take pains to affect our ſelves deeply with that Truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning another Life, which our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> hath revealed; and to the belief of which we have been educated in his Church. And if we have leſs prejudice againſt theſe Doctrines than the <hi>Jews</hi> had, and yet are ſwallowed up with this World as much as they were, we are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40809:50"/> but the more inexcuſable. So that undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly the advantage we have over them, ſhould make us the more concerned to lay theſe things to heart; becauſe we are ſo much the more to blame, if knowing theſe things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt from our Infancy, we do not practiſe accordingly.</p>
                  <p>Nay, when the Profeſſion of the True Faith does bring in Worldly Advantages, there ſeems to be as much (if not more) reaſon to reflect in this manner upon our ſelves, as when nothing was to be gotten by it in this World, but the loſs of all things. We are then doubtleſs to remember, that the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt is not of this World,</hi> and that the good things of this Life are not the Rewards which he hath promiſed; but that by ſetting our Hearts inordinately upon that worldly Eaſe and Profit which we enjoy by the Profeſſion of true Chriſtianity, we are in the way of loſing that Fruit thereof which will laſt for ever, and the hope of which was all that our Lord uſed to invite Men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>If we follow Chriſt for the Loaves, we ſhall forſake him when we find our ſelves diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, as the <hi>Jews</hi> at <hi>Capernaum</hi> did, and take Occaſions and Pretences ſo to do as eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they, and ſome of his own Diſciples found them. For we are not to think, that that Saying, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. was the true cauſe of their going off from him,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40809:51"/> but only ſuch a plauſible Occaſion as they had a good while waited for. The reaſon of their Offence, at the bottom, was, that they had long ſince perceived our Saviour was not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſatisfie their worldly Expectations, and they did not believe it worth their while to follow him for a Reward in another Life; which Prejudice againſt him had deſtroyed all their Faith, as he told them himſelf, <hi>There are ſome among you that believe not,</hi> Verſ. 64. They were thoſe that ſaid, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 60. <hi>This is an hard Saying, who can hear it?</hi> For it is not ſaid that <hi>All,</hi> but only, <hi>Many of his Diſciples when they had heard this, ſaid, This is an hard,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> Thoſe very Men of whom he ſaid, <hi>But there are ſome among you that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not,</hi> Verſ. 64. <hi>i. e.</hi> who had followed him for worldly Advantages, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did from the <hi>Wilderneſs to Capernaum:</hi> Of whom our Lord ſaid the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>they believed not,</hi> Verſ. 36. For though but the day before they had <hi>acknowledged him to be the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that was to come into the World,</hi> yet find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was likely to diſappoint their worldly Hopes, they preſently changed their Opinion of him. So that a ſincere Aim at Everlaſting Life is very neceſſary even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a conſtant Belief and Profeſſion of the Faith.</p>
                  <p>And much more to a Practice anſwerable to it; which will, as I ſaid before, be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not a little, if we will uſe our ſelves to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40809:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> conſider what care we at for theſe mortal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and this worldly Life; and what reaſon there is to be incomparably more concerned for a bleſſed Reſurrection to Eternal Life; which I make not the leaſt doubt, is the great Inſtruction we are to learn from theſe figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Diſcourſes of our bleſſed Saviour. And if we conſtantly have it in our Eye, it will not not only render the <hi>meaning</hi> of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter very <hi>plain,</hi> but the <hi>reading</hi> of it, if we ſhould read it every day we live, very <hi>uſeful</hi> to us.</p>
                  <p>And indeed, thoſe parts of God's Word which are purpoſely deſigned to work in us a deep Concern for <hi>Everlaſting Life,</hi> ought to be very preſent to our Minds, and to dwell richly in us, that we may be always well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to reſiſt the Temptations of the World. For which Reaſons we ſhould often think of thoſe Leſſons of our Saviour; <hi>Lay not up for your ſelves Treaſure upon Earth, where Moth and Ruſt doth corrupt, and where Thieves break through and ſteal: But lay up for your ſelves Treaſure in Heaven, where neither Moth,</hi> &amp;c. And, <hi>Be not afraid of them that kill the Body, and after that have no more that they can do. But I will forewarn you whom ye ſhall fear: Fear him, which after he hath killed, hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to caſt into Hell: yea, I ſay unto you, fear him.</hi> And that in this Chapter; <hi>Labour not for the Meat which periſheth, bat for that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40809:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> which endureth to everlaſting Life, which the Son of Man ſhall give unto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Rules ſeeming at firſt ſight to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge us of all Care for our <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> in this World, St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> thought it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to obſerve upon the laſt of them, that our Lord did not intend to countenance <hi>Lazineſs,</hi> who himſelf ſaid, It is more <hi>Bleſſed to give than to receive:</hi> And that St. <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Man to <hi>work with his hands the thing that is good, that he may have to give to him that needeth.</hi> But ſince theſe Exhortations run, as if we were to be <hi>abſolutely</hi> uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned about this Life, no queſtion but that care of Eternal Life is preſcribed; in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to which, our Cares for this World ſhould ſeem nothing at all. Therefore when we deſire our appointed Food, we ſhould think how much more it is our Intereſt to <hi>hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>that Meat which endureth to everlaſting Life.</hi> And when we moſt of all feel the hopes and fears of things that go no farther than this World, we cannot entertain a better Thought than this, that if we are ſo much concerned for this Life, how careful ought we to be not to miſs of Eternal Salvation?</p>
                  <p>Which kind of Reflections are the more neceſſary for us, the more deeply we are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in this World. For we do not only <hi>labour for the meat that periſhes,</hi> that is, for juſt enough to ſerve the Neceſſities of Life;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40809:52"/> but we would be at eaſe beſide, and live in reaſonable Plenty, and enjoy what is conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the Pleaſure, as well as the Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Life: and there are very few that know when to make an end of multiplying Riches, when once they are got into the way of Encreaſe. But are we thus concerned for an end of infinitely greater Moment? Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do not theſe very worldly Cares reprove our negligence about better and greater things, while perhaps we do no more towards our Salvation, than to avoid the groſſeſt Sins of all, but take little thought how to <hi>grow in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The whole Strain of our Saviour's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in this Chapter, naturally leads to ſuch Conſiderations as theſe: And if we mind them in good Earneſt, they will, by the Grace of God, moderate our Affections and Cares about this World in the firſt place; and then leave all that Concern for preſent and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory good things, which we cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as a perpetual Admonition, to be much more thoughtful for our everlaſting Salvation, and to make it the greateſt buſineſs of our Lives, by <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>good Works,</hi> to lay up for our ſelves Treaſure in Heaven, and to lay the ſtreſs of our Comfort whilſt we are here, in the joyful hope of being <hi>raiſed up at the laſt day to live for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40809:53"/>
                  <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>SInce theſe Papers were almoſt Printed off, I met with Dr. <hi>Godden</hi>'s Sermon upon St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Day; in which he endeavours, from ſome Paſſages in this Chapter, to infer the ſubſtantial Change of the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> into the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> But upon the moſt Impartial Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that I can make of his Performance, I do not find that he offers any colour of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his Concluſion, which I have not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. And therefore inſtead of ſtopping theſe Papers for the ſake of his Sermon, I think it fair enough to ſay to him, and to the World, that I can ſee no reaſon obliging me to do it.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:53"/>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE OF HUMANITY AND CHARITY.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>GAL. VI.10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all Men, eſpecially unto them that are of the Houſhold of Faith.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>By <hi>W. CLAGET,</hi> D. D.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the <hi>Golden Lion,</hi> and <hi>T. Newborough</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1693.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:54"/>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:40809:54"/>
                  <head>A DISCOURSE OF Humanity and Charity.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>GAL. VI.10.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all Men, eſpecially unto them that are of the Houſhold of Faith.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>FROM theſe Words I might well take occaſion to diſcourſe upon three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Subjects.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First;</hi> Of the ſeveral <hi>Acts</hi> or <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of Charity, which are here all comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40809:55"/> under <hi>doing good;</hi> although by the 6th Verſe it ſhould ſeem, that the Charity of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating</hi> in the <hi>good things</hi> of this World, was principally intended in this place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly;</hi> Of the <hi>Objects</hi> of Charity; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which the Text expreſly affirms, that they are <hi>all Men</hi> in general, but eſpecially the <hi>Houſhould of Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, <hi>Thirdly;</hi> Of the <hi>Rewards</hi> of Charity, which are intimated in the Text by the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of thoſe words, <hi>As we have therefore opportunity,</hi> in the foregoing Promiſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>In due ſeaſon we ſhall reap if we faint not.</hi> For this ſhews the <hi>Opportunity</hi> here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to be the time that we have for <hi>ſowing</hi> our good Works; and that if we uſe it, they will yield a Harveſt of Rewards, which we ſhall certainly <hi>reap</hi> in due ſeaſon.</p>
                  <p>But in ſo narrow a compaſs of time, I muſt not undertake to enlarge upon theſe three Particulars; and therefore omitting the Firſt, I chuſe to inſiſt upon the Second, and to conclude with ſome few Reflections upon the laſt.</p>
                  <p>And thus the firſt thing to be conſidered is, the Exhortation to <hi>doing Good,</hi> with reſpect to the general Object: Let us do good unto <hi>all Men.</hi> Now, becauſe it is impoſſible that we ſhould be actually beneficent to every
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40809:55"/> Man in the World, otherwiſe than by our Prayers for All: Therefore the plain meaning of the Exhortation is this, that we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude no Man out of our Charity, who needs our Help, and comes within the Compaſs of our Ability to do him good. Which tho it be a Duty ſo much for the Intereſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that one would think no body ſhould be againſt it; yet as the World goes, it ſeems to need the Charity of us All, in ſtanding up for it againſt all falſe Principles, and bad Examples, that are advanced in oppoſition to it.</p>
                  <p>I muſt be content at this time to ſpeak for it, without reflecting upon any Opinions or Practices that are againſt it. And therefore I proceed forthwith to repreſent this part of the Apoſtle's Exhortation, <hi>To do good unto all,</hi> as a Duty under Obligations common to <hi>all Men,</hi> and under Obligations peculiar to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">I. The Obligations of the firſt ſort, are <hi>Common Humanity,</hi> and <hi>Natural Piety.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Common Humanity.</hi> For the ſenſe of that Nature which is common to us All, does oblige us to bear kind Affection one to another. Becauſe I know how I my ſelf am affected with Pain and Poverty, with Hunger and Thirſt, with Fear and Grief, and with all the Sufferings that Humane Life is ſubject to; I know how others are affected with
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40809:56"/> them too, inaſmuch as we are All moulded into one and the ſame Nature: So that <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> it ſelf has given me a ſenſe of the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of others, which had been a trouble without any Advantage, if ſhe had not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhewn me the way to eaſe my ſelf, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them. And that we are framed to theſe Affections, is one of the nobleſt Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges we have above <hi>Brutes,</hi> who were made for Selfiſhneſs, becauſe they do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and cannot feel what their Fellow-Brutes ſuffer. For as for thoſe appearances of Kindneſs which the Author of Nature hath diſpoſed them to, eſpecially of the old ones to their young, we ſee they proceed from an Impulſe, the meaning of which they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, becauſe they go off by certain Rules; for when the young ones can ſhift for themſelves, there is no appearance of Compaſſion afterwards in the old, whatſoever occaſion there may be for it. To <hi>Man</hi> only of all Creatures under Heaven, God has giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en this quality, to be affected with the Grief and with the Joy of thoſe of his own kind; and to feel the Evils which others feel, that we may be univerſally diſpoſed to help and relieve one another.</p>
                  <p>Now this, no leſs than other moral Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, is under the power of our own Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to improve it, or weaken it. Tho' <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> inclines us to Humanity, yet <hi>Custom</hi> and <hi>bad Principles</hi> may give us another <hi>Bias,</hi>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:40809:56"/> and make us unconcern'd what others feel. But Nature, without Art and Force uſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, ſeldom proves cruel; and we ſee that they which have the leaſt of that we call <hi>Breeding,</hi> are prone to Pity and Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration. Men of a ſimple and ruſtick Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and of mean Profeſſions, eaſily fall into Compaſſion; and ſeldom fail of relieving one another, if the conſideration of their own Intereſt does not prevail againſt it.</p>
                  <p>But where Humane Nature meets with the beſt Improvements, there Humanity grows into generous Inclinations. The more that Men are exalted above Brutes, the more that they are framed to other Vertues, to Wiſdom, Patience, and Fidelity, and Temperance, and Fortitude, and Modeſty; ſo much the more are they addicted to Mercy and Compaſſion, and forward to relieve others, tho' with loſs and pain to themſelves. But Inhumanity grows evermore upon the Corruption of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by wretched Miſtakes, by bruitiſh Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, or by Pride and Inſolence. It grows no where but in a Soil that is already curſed. And ſometimes there muſt be a Complication of all manner of Vices to make way for this. For ſome Men who are not otherwiſe good, are not yet bad enough to put off Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their own kind.</p>
                  <p>Finally, That Applauſe and Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is univerſally given to Men of a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent and generous Temper, is a ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40809:57"/> that to do good to All, is the Law of our Nature. Nay, the Commendation given to <hi>Vertue,</hi> is in great part owing to this, that every Vertue is beneficial not only to him that hath it, but to others too. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is <hi>lovely,</hi> and of <hi>good Report</hi> amongſt Men, as all Vertue is, takes the name of Goodneſs, becauſe it partakes of its Nature, and ſerves its End: Inſomuch that <hi>Juſtice</hi> it it ſelf has it's Praiſe from <hi>Goodneſs and Mercy.</hi> The Severity of the Laws againſt Villains, and the Puniſhments inflicted on them, being not ſo much approved for the Pain that they ſuffer, as for the Inſtruction of the Example, and the Security it brings to honeſt Men. In ſhort, tho' Greatneſs will be always flattered, yet nothing is more evident, than that Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Goodneſs only, will be approved and loved; whilſt Unmercifulneſs and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, how common ſoever the practice of it may be, is yet counted <hi>unnatural,</hi> and is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſo hated a thing, that they who are moſt guilty of it, will call Impudence to their Aid, as long as it will ſerve the turn, to purge themſelves to the World, by denying the Fact.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Natural Piety</hi> does no leſs bind us to do good to <hi>all,</hi> than common Humanity. For we are taught ſo to do, not only by what we know concerning our ſelves, but by all that we know of God.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:40809:57"/>
                  <p>As he has made us all in one Nature, ſo he hath made a common proviſion for us all, of things needful for our Life and Welfare. He has given us ſpace and room enough to live in, and the Sun, and the Rain, and the Fruits of the Earth to ſerve us all, and all things convenient and comfortable in plenty, ſufficient for the whole Race of Mankind; a plain ſign of his Goodneſs to us all, and a plain Inſtruction that he would have us live without Envy and Rapine, and be inoffenſive and kind, and where need requires, liberal to one another.</p>
                  <p>And yet in the midſt of this common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion he hath ſtill left us in need of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Aſſiſtance; and even the greateſt of All for many Comforts of Life; nay, for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſary ſupports of it, to depend upon the meaneſt, as theſe do, for other Benefits, depend upon thoſe above them; that ſo this mutual dependance we have upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might be a further obligation to a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Affection, and that Benefits given and returned might always cheriſh and improve it.</p>
                  <p>Farther; Inaſmuch as God hath derived us all from one Stock, and made us of one Blood; this ſeems to ſpeak his Intention of obliging all Men to mutual Beneficence. He could as eaſily have peopled the World at firſt, as he created one Man, and out of that Man took a Woman, to be the Parents of Mankind.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40809:58"/> But he rather choſe that we ſhould be the Children of one Stock, that remembring how we were All once in the Loins of one Parent, we ſhould as Brethren love and help one another.</p>
                  <p>To conclude this Argument; There is no Perſwaſion concerning God more deeply root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our Natures, than that he is good and gracious, full of Compaſſion, and ready to help the Miſerable. For we are made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this ſo ſtrongly, that no Opinions which imply the contrary, can utterly extinguiſh this Faith. For they that think the hardeſt things of God, do in effect confeſs their own Miſtakes, by praying always to him, and with more earneſt Applications, when they fall into Diſtreſs. But is it not evident, that God by leaving ſuch Impreſſions of his own Goodneſs upon our Minds, ſignified his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that we ſhould be good to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, under the penalty of being odious to him?</p>
                  <p>Such things as theſe may be ſaid, to ſhew the common Obligations we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to do good to All, as we are <hi>Men.</hi> But then,</p>
                  <p n="2">II. There are peculiar Obligations to it as we are <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> I will be bold to ſay, that if Chriſtianity had deſtroyed the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Humanity, it had been a terrible Temptation to a good Man to reject it;
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40809:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> Nay, if it had not eſtabliſhed and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them, we had wanted one conſiderable Inducement to receive it. For there is ſo much natural Evidence that Men are bound to do good to one another, that I doubt no Evidence can be great enough that a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion comes from God, which lets Men looſe from all the Obligations of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And if there be any other Character of Doctrine, which would induce a Man to receive it as coming from God, more than another, it is this, That it doth effectually promote Benignity and Charity, a kind and generous Temper, and all ſorts of good Works. And this I am ſure is the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of true and uncorrupted Chriſtianity. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As it is a Rule of Manners, it is whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly framed to deſtroy all Diſpoſitions to Rage, Malice, Cruelty, and Uncharitableneſs; and to plain Goodneſs, Compaſſion and Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in our Minds. To this end it hath provided againſt all the Cauſes of Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs; that is, againſt Covetouſneſs, Luſt, Ambition, Impatience, Revengefulneſs, and the like. And therefore the Apoſtle doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to ſay, that <hi>the end of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Charity.</hi> And that which is moſt remarkable in this kind is, That whereas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can with greater colour of Reaſon ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40809:59"/> the Diſpoſition of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to be good to All Men, than to be himſelf abuſed and wronged by others; therefore our Lord, to guard the Duty of Univerſal Beneficence, has made it our Duty to forgive; nay, and to love our very Enemies; which ſeems to be a Law peculiar to Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If we conſider our Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the Author of our Religion, he was the moſt glorious Pattern of Charity and doing good, that ever appeared in the World. For he was contented to come down into this wretched World, and to lead an afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life, and to endure an ignominious and painful Death, for the Salvation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And when he converſed publickly amongſt his Country-men, he <hi>went about do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good:</hi> And though his Doctrine and his Works were ſtill cavilled at, and perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a wrong Intention, by a froward and unthankful Generation of <hi>Men,</hi> yet he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to do good to all that came to him for Relief; and to many others that never ſought it from him. So that we are to treat every Man, as one whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo loved, as to die for him. And if our Religion ſtands at all in the imitation of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we are to do good to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankful</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,</hi> as need requires; nay, and to <hi>do Good againſt Evil,</hi> and if poſſible, <hi>to overcome Evil with Good.</hi> But,</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:40809:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>3. The way which he choſe for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of his Religion, was above all things a Demonſtration, that he intended his Diſciples ſhould be inoffenſive and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent to all Men. If indeed under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſaving the Souls of Men, he had armed his Followers to kill his Enemies, his Doctrine had not carried ſo much as a face of Sincerity, but had rather looked like a Deſign of Intereſt and Ambition, than of Charity and doing good. But with what Weapons did he ſend abroad his Miniſters to ſubdue Men to himſelf? <hi>Go,</hi> ſays he, <hi>cleanſe the Leper, heal the Sick,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 10.7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>raiſe the Dead,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give.</hi> If this would not make their preaching effectual, the worſt they were to do was,<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> to <hi>ſhake the Duſt off their Feet</hi> againſt that place which rejected them.<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> If they were <hi>perſecute in one City,</hi> they were to <hi>flee to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> If Sufferings followed them from one place to another, they were to <hi>poſſeſs their Souls in patience;</hi> and, in all this, to <hi>love and pray for their Enemies.</hi> The Doctrine of our Lord JESUS, and his own Example, and the Means he uſed to ſpread his Faith in the World, were all of a piece; that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity being eminently preached in the way of converting the World to his Religion, which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40809:60"/> was ſo powerfully recommended by his Example, and ſo ſtrongly urged by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And if it had not been ſo, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> had not done ſo much good, as the way of propagating it had done Miſchief. The Doctrine it ſelf, of <hi>doing good to All,</hi> had been but a dead Letter, if it had been carried into the World with Rage, and Cruelty; It had ſerved only to condemn <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of Hypocriſie, for pretending the good of Mens Souls in deſtroying their Lives; and for pretending Charity, while they carried Confuſion and Deſolation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they went. Had they behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this manner, they had given juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion that they were gathering a Party in an hoſtile oppoſition to all the World beſides, and that the <hi>Brotherly-kindneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> conſiſted in excluding the reſt of Mankind from common Charity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that Unbelievers ſhould be treated as Enemies, and proſecuted with the utmoſt Hatred. And therefore altho in this very place St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s deſign was to move the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to contribute towards the common Concerns of the Church; yet leſt he ſhould ſeem to exempt them from the obligation of <hi>doing good to All,</hi> by calling for their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence towards one another; he prevents the ſcandal by requiring Beneficence to <hi>All,</hi> almoſt out of its place. I ſay, though his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40809:60"/> buſineſs was now to perſwade them to <hi>do good to the Houſhold of Faith:</hi> Yet that this might be no pretence for Inhumanity, he guards his meaning by an Exhortation in the firſt place, to do good to <hi>all Men.</hi> And upon all theſe Accounts, I had much rather at the laſt Day, bear the Judgment of an <hi>Heathen</hi> that is endued with Humanity and Mercy, than of a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, let him have what he will elſe. And thus much for the general Object of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Duty of doing Good to All Men.</p>
                  <p>The Second is more particular, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Houſhold of Faith;</hi> and upon this the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation runs thus; let us do good, <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the Houſhold of Faith;</hi> that is, <hi>to Chriſtians,</hi> who are one Body or Society of Men, united one to another under one Head, our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by <hi>one Faith,</hi> to the Profeſſion of which they are admitted by <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi> according to that Saying of the Apoſtle, <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4.5.</note> which are the Bonds that make the Church one Family or <hi>Houſhold.</hi> Now to all that are of this Houſhold, we are to do good <hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,</hi> and more than to others, though we are to do good to <hi>all</hi> Men. And under this Particular there are theſe two things obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:40809:61"/>1. That the Obligation we are under to do good to <hi>all</hi> Men, does not hinder <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring ſome before others,</hi> whether in reſpect of the Time, or the degree of doing good. I obſerved before, that we have ſo limited a Power, that we cannot be actually bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent to All, and therefore muſt chooſe our Objects with Diſcretion. There are ſeveral good Works which many do not need from us, and we cannot perform them for All that do. And therefore Charity muſt be guided by Judgment in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining upon whom to let fall the effects of our readineſs to do good to All. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that Relation we have to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is neareſt, is to derermine the Caſe. If I can provide only for my own Family, they are in the firſt place to be taken care for. And where the Caſe is in other Reſpects equal, I am to prefer an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance before a Stranger; my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man before a Foreigner; a Friend before an Enemy; a ſerviceable Man before one that is good for nothing; and a Vertuous Man before a Villain. But the Caſe may be ſuch, and the need ſo much more preſſing on the one ſide than the other, that I may be obliged to prefer the later before the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And as to this matter, when all is ſaid that can be ſaid, the Prudence of every
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40809:61"/> honeſt Man will be requiſite to apply general Rules to particular Caſes. Thus much is implied in this part of the Exhortation. But,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This is expreſſed, That whereas there are certain Reaſons of making a difference, in doing good between Man and Man; we ſhould have a very ſpecial regard to thoſe that profeſs the true Religion, and are Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Body with us as Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that common relation we have to them in the great Body of Mankind; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if their Converſation be as it becomes the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which I queſtion not is ſuppoſed by the Apoſtle, who would not have had a diſorderly Liver ſo much as continued in the Houſhold of Faith; and more eſpecially if their Neceſſities be great and preſſing; and moſt of all when it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that they fare ill for doing well, which is a Caſe that often happens. Tho' ſuch Men be none of our Kindred, tho' they be none of our Country, they are yet allied to us by more Sacred Ties, by a near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Relation, by ſtricter Bonds; and that we are to do good to them more than to others, is a point that ſtands upon plain and ſtrong Reaſons.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:40809:62"/>
                  <p>For, 1. It is very fit and juſt that we ſhould <hi>love them</hi> more than others; For they are really better than other Men are; and if upon this Account they deſerve a greater Intereſt in our <hi>Affection,</hi> they ought to have a proportionable ſhare in the uſual Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Teſtimonies of it. When our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid, <hi>By this ſhall all Men know that ye are my Diſciples,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 13.35.</note> 
                     <hi>if ye have Love one to another,</hi> we muſt needs think that he meant a more fervent and generous Affection than is at the bottom of the common Friendſhips of the World, and more effectual and lively Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of it, then are uſually ſeen amongſt other Men: For otherwiſe, how ſhould their <hi>Love</hi> diſtinguiſh them from thoſe which were not his Diſciples? But was this Extraordinary Affection and Beneficence no better than meer Fondneſs and Partiality? Was it not to be grounded upon Wiſdom and Judgment, and to be juſtified by the true Worth and Excellence of his Followers? The Diſciples of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were to be Examples of Fidelity and Juſtice, Humility and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, Patience and Meekneſs, and Faith in God, and likewiſe of Charity to Men. God himſelf loves Men for ſuch Qualities as theſe are, and will reward them for ever. And therefore how is it poſſible but for the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40809:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſake of theſe Qualities they ſhould love one another, and ſhew it by the effects of true Eſteem and Affection, in doing Good to Men thus qualified, above others. And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Tis a very neceſſary Expreſſion of <hi>Love to our Lord Jeſus,</hi> to make this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in favour of his faithful Servants and Followers. He has made them Members of Himſelf, and as ſuch he will treat them; and therefore he expects that we ſhould do ſo too, as we undoubtedly ſhall, if we are true and living Members of his Body our ſelves. <hi>If ye love me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>keep my Commandments.</hi> And, <hi>This is the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he hath given us, that we love one another;</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> tells us with much ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, and lays great weight upon it. But if it had not been urged in this manner, no Inference from our Love to <hi>Jeſus</hi> could be more natural, than to bear a ſpecial kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards thoſe whom he is pleaſed to own not only for his Servants, but his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and his Friends. The truth is, he hath left them to receive the lively Expreſſions of our real Affection to him. And it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that although we ſhall be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to him for our Behaviour to all Men, yet he hath told us before-hand that a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular regard will be had at our laſt Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how we have comforted and relieved
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40809:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Servants in their Diſtreſs. For upon that Charge, that thoſe on the Left-hand had not given him <hi>Meat</hi> when he was <hi>hungry,</hi> nor <hi>Drink</hi> when he was <hi>thirſty;</hi> nor <hi>clothed</hi> him when he was <hi>naked,</hi> nor <hi>viſited</hi> him when he was <hi>ſick</hi> and in <hi>Priſon;</hi> it is added, <hi>Then ſhall they ſay, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, and gave thee no meat,</hi> &amp;c. And then ſhall he anſwer them, ſaying, <hi>Verily, inaſmuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not unto me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Our Charity ſhould run more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in this Channel, for the relief of good Chriſtians; becauſe in their Diſtreſs, <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only upon God for help,</hi> and expect in it ſuch ways only as God approves. But they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford to help themſelves by wicked or indirect means. We therefore ſhould take our ſelves to be God's Miniſters in bringing Succour to them; that whilſt they have the Honour to approve their Dependance upon him, by refuſing all ways of Relief which are inconſiſtent with their Duty to him, we may have the honour to let them ſee that they have not truſted God in vain. We ſhould conſider true Believers and good Men, when they are oppreſſed with Want, as under an effectual Reſtraint from all baſe and impious ways of ſupplying themſelves; and conſequently as the nobleſt Objects of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40809:63"/> Charity; of Charity, I ſay; for the Charity of ſome Good Men is the uſual way by which God relieves other Good Men in their Afflictions. It may ſometimes be a good Reaſon to relieve a Beggar, that we may prevent his taking a worſe Courſe to relieve himſelf. But Charity ſhould never flow more plentifully than to thoſe that will not be ſtarved out of their Integrity, but truſt God though they die. And that,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe the end of Charity is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attained by having a ſpecial regard to ſuch Perſons, in doing Good to them, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and more than, to others: for here is not only Good done to Men that are in Want and Diſtreſs, which is common to the Relief both of the Good and the Bad; but here is <hi>an encouragement given to Vertue too,</hi> which is peculiar to the Caſe of doing Good to Good Men. And therefore, beſides what is done in meer Humanity, there ſhould be ſomething added as a Reward to Vertue. And we ought to remember, that God in giving us more or leſs power to be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to Men, has thereby put it into our Power to encourage Piety and good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and all that is worthy of Praiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men. And whilſt we make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the World, that Righteous Men
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40809:64"/> are in their Diſtreſs ſo far from being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of God, that not only their Diſtreſs, but their Innocence too, and their Vertue, ſhall be conſidered by Men; we do effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reprove Wickedneſs and Vice, and preach Honeſty and Piety. And it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely but Charity thus placed, beſides the Good that it does to the Bodies of ſome, will do good alſo to the Souls of others.</p>
                  <p>Upon ſuch plain Reaſons as theſe, we ſhould <hi>more eſpecially</hi> do Good to the <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of Faith.</hi> Whereby alſo we may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther trouble avoid their Cenſures, who carry their Reſpect to thoſe whom God loves and honours beyond what I have been pleading for: I mean thoſe who reckon it to be no ſmall Act of Piety, to viſit the Bones, and the Aſhes, and other Reliques of Saints and Martyrs, and to leave coſtly Preſents at their Shrines and Sepulchres. For it has been laid to our Charge with no little Confidence, that we diſhonour and contemn the dead Servants of God, becauſe we do not thus offer to 'em. But we may, I hope, clear our ſelves without offence, and ſay that we are as ready to honour the Dead, as to relieve the Living Saints. We are not well aſſured that the Bones and the Utenſils, to which ſo mighty a Regard is given, are indeed the Remains of Saints: But if we
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40809:64"/> were, yet we are not ſatisfied that there is any reſpect to the dead Bodies of the Saints, beyond that of a decent and honourable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment, warranted by the Examples of the truly Primitive Church; and that any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to 'em beyond this is acceptable to God, has wanted Proof hitherto, and Defence as well as Proof. But now we are very ſure that the Bodies of Righteous and Godly Men, are holy, and the living <hi>Temples of God,</hi> whilſt they live with us in this World: For this the Scripture ſaith. We are ſure that the Sacrifices of <hi>Alms,</hi> which are <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> when given for God's ſake, that with them, I ſay, <hi>God is well-pleaſed;</hi> for this is affirmed in the Scripture. We are very ſure that they are doubly pleaſing to him, when they are preſented to his living Members, when they are diſtributed to the <hi>Houſhold of Faith;</hi> for this alſo is according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And in all theſe things there is ſuch evident Congruity, that Reaſon without any Diſpute preſently agrees to 'em. In a word, I do not read that any the leaſt Promiſe is made to viſiting and preſenting the Aſhes of the Dead; nor that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will take theſe things when done in honour of his Servants, as done to himſelf. But I read that at the laſt day, our having <hi>viſited,</hi> and <hi>relieved,</hi> our <hi>feeding, clothing,</hi> and <hi>comforting</hi> the leaſt of his true Servants that are with us, will be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40809:65"/> ſo accounted, and will be rewarded, as if theſe things had been done to himſelf. <hi>In as much as ye did it to the leaſt of theſe, ye did it alſo unto me.</hi> All which being conſidered, we may be ſure that we are well guarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the angry Reflections of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, if we take care to excel them in Charity to the <hi>Living,</hi> as much as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin they out-do us in honouring the <hi>Dead.</hi> And thus much for the Objects of Charity, as they are ſpecified in the Text.</p>
                  <p>I am now to touch upon that Intimation of the Rewards of it, which we have in the Text alſo: <hi>As we have opportunity.</hi> It is a true ſence of theſe words to interpret them thus; as often as occaſions of Charity preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and as long as we are in a condition to do good Works of this kind. But as I told you, they have a plain reference to the three foregoing Verſes; <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked: for whatſoever a Man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap. For he that ſoweth to the Fleſh, ſhall of the Fleſh reap Corruption: but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, ſhall of the Spirit reap Life everlaſting. And let us not be weary in well-doing; for in due ſeaſon we ſhall reap, if we faint not. As we have therefore opportunity, let us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> as long as the opportunity or ſeaſon of ſowing in good Works laſts, let us ſow, that we may reap plentifully when Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt-time
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40809:65"/> comes, <hi>i. e.</hi> when the Rewards of Charity ſhall be given abroad, as they will aſſuredly be in a better World, if not in this alſo. The <hi>Seed</hi> which he means, as we find by the 6th Verſe, are the good things of this Life. And as by <hi>ſowing to the Spirit,</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly meant, doing good out of our worldly Store to All Men, and eſpecially to the <hi>Houſhold of Faith;</hi> ſo by <hi>ſowing to the Fleſh,</hi> muſt on the other hand be meant, the encreaſing of our own Poſſeſſions, and the ſerving of our own Pleaſures: I will not ſay providing for inordinate Luſts; for this is more than the Text neceſſarily implies, tho' that be <hi>ſowing to the Fleſh too?</hi> So that we will ſet that aſide, and conſider what the uſe of that Wealth will come to, which is expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in things not to be blamed, in goodly Houſes, and fine Cloaths, and a plentiful Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the like. For this is <hi>ſowing to the Fleſh;</hi> and the Apoſtle tells us, that he <hi>that ſoweth to the Fleſh, ſhall of the Fleſh reap Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption;</hi> i. e. at the end of this Life he ſhall find, that all theſe things have <hi>periſhed in the uſing,</hi> and can turn to no account for him now at laſt, that there is no farther enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them; and that the very remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them, which is all that is left, hath neither Pleaſure nor Profit in it: And ſo he ſhall reap for this ſowing, nothing but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Corruption, <hi>i. e.</hi> no increaſe, but a loſs of what he ſowed.</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:40809:66"/>
                  <p>Now true it is, that thus we muſt all ſow to the Fleſh in ſome degree or other, we muſt provide for our own Bodies, and the needs of our Life; and we may make a reaſonable uſe of our Wealth, for the innocent Pleaſures of it too. But this is that ſowing, which will yield no Harveſt at laſt. There is an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment for the time, but when the uſe is over, there is no farther Profit to be expected. So that he is ſaid by the Apoſtle, to ſow to the Fleſh, who does little or nothing elſe with the good things of this World that God has given him, but only ſets himſelf out with them, and applies them wholly to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his own Needs and Pleaſures. For by him that ſoweth to the Spirit, he could not mean one that makes no uſe of his Wealth for ſupplying his own Needs and Neceſſities, but one who does that, and relieves others too. Now of him it is ſaid, that he ſhall reap Life everlaſting; for tho' the Seed be it ſelf of a tranſitory, carnal and periſhing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet being thus diſpoſed to a ſpiritual uſe, being caſt into ſuch a Soil, it ſhall yield an everlaſting Profit, and an Increaſe that he ſhall live upon it for ever. But then ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked; for as a Man ſoweth, he ſhall alſo reap.</hi> Tho' <hi>a Cup of cold Water given to a Diſciple, in the name of a Diſciple, ſhall not loſe its Reward,</hi> i. e. when either more is not in the hand of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40809:66"/> him that gives, or no farther need in him that receives, yet ſo ſmall a thing is Mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where there is greater need on the one ſide, and ability to anſwer it on the other. This being remembred, it remains true what our Saviour ſaid, <hi>He that receiveth;</hi> and therefore he that relieveth <hi>a Righteous Man, in the name of a Righteous Man,</hi> or becauſe he is a Righteous Man, <hi>ſhall receive a Righteous Man's Reward.</hi> For to him in ſome part the Righteous Man's Thankfulneſs to God, and the ſupport of his Faith and Dependence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and the making of his perſeverance therein more eaſie, and the reſcuing him out of Temptation, may in good meaſure be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</p>
                  <p>Now Brethren, we have in this Life only the opportunity of ſowing to the Spirit in this manner, and of making Friends to our ſelves of the <hi>Mammon</hi> of this World, that when it fails, <hi>we may be received into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Habitations,</hi> and of turning the things of this World, which ſo often <hi>betray Men to Perdition,</hi> into the Inſtruments of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Let us therefore often conſider thoſe Words and Exhortations of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and that when our Reckoning comes to be caſt up at the end of our Lives, there will be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger any Profit or Comfort in what we have worn, and eaten, and drank; but we ſhall
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40809:67"/> find that to be true, <hi>The Belly for Meats, and Meats for the Belly; but God will deſtroy both it and them.</hi> But that the remembrance of the Good we have done to <hi>All Men,</hi> and <hi>eſpecially to the Houſhold of Faith,</hi> will be ſweet and pleaſant to us, and that the Reward of it will endure for ever.</p>
                  <q>Therefore my beloved Brethren, be ye sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know that your Labour is not in vain in the Lord.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:40809:67"/>
                  <head>A LETTER CONCERNING <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Charity to <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Publiſhed by <hi>W. Claget,</hi> D. D.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Find that the Tranſlation of the <hi>Whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Advices from the Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> &amp;c. which may have help'd to ſettle the Minds of others, has ſomething diſcompos'd yours. For though you are not, I dare ſay, pleas'd with the <hi>Proteſtant Preface</hi> to it, yet however you diſſemble your pain, Wiſe Men ſay, that you bite that <hi>Preface</hi> for grief of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40809:68"/> the <hi>Tranſlation.</hi> I cannot but admire the Art of you Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in running down Books with bold Contempt, which you know not otherwiſe how to deal with. This <hi>Tranſlation</hi> and <hi>Preface,</hi> for ſome Reaſons, is an Eye-ſore to you; and chiefly for helping to ſpoil the new Faſhion of maintaining <hi>Popery</hi> by <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> it. Something therefore muſt be done with it; and ſo a little part of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face,</hi> which did not belong neither to the main Deſign of the Book, muſt be ſingled out, and be made an Example. As for all the reſt, 'tis ſufficiently anſwer'd by ſaying, <hi>Muſt I ſet up for Reader of Anatomy upon all the Pamphlets that come into the World? I am highly obliged to you for the Kindneſs; but I think the Scavenger has much the better Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who has nothing but Dirt and Sinks to deal with, much leſs offenſive, than to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways raking into filthy Calumnies, fulſom In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruities, and noyſom Impertinencies.</hi> Which kind of Language one would hardly uſe, but out of a great deſire to be unanſwerable one way or other. After this touch upon the whole, you come to <hi>touch at ſome Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars which ſeem to fall within your Province of Repreſenting;</hi> or rather to touch at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which you were the better provided to touch, becauſe you had in the very ſame manner toucht it before in your <hi>Fourth Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40809:68"/> of the Firſt Part.</hi> The Particular is, That <hi>Papiſts</hi> allow no leſs a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> than <hi>Protestants</hi> do to <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Now although this is all that I am concerned to oppoſe, yet I ſhall offer a few Words to your Preparatory Diſcourſe, in which you pretend to ſhew what good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon you have to pronounce againſt the <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of Salvation amongſt us; or rather in the new faſhion'd Phraſe, that we as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> are guilty of <hi>Sins inconſiſtent with Salvation,</hi> inaſmuch as we are ſeparated from your Communion, The ſhort of what you ſay is, <hi>That after most ſerious Conſiderations and the weighing of all Reaſons,</hi> the <hi>Papiſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>in which he is, to be</hi> that one only holy Catholick Church, and therefore he <hi>does not queſtion, but what is truly affirm'd of the Church of the Apoſtles and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages, and thoſe that fell from it, is moſt true of the ſame Church now in being, of which he is a Member, and of all thoſe who ſeparate from it, upon what Pretext ſoever.</hi> Now it had been much more to the purpoſe to have produc'd thoſe ſerious Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than to have ſpent ſo much time as you did, to prove what none of us make the leaſt Queſtion of, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd a Catholick Church; that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Care of it to the Apoſtles; that they were inſpir'd with the knowledge of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40809:69"/> Truth; that they left Paſtors to govern and feed the Flock after their Deceaſe; and that the Promiſe of Salvation is made to Believers, excluſively to Unbelievers. This I ſay, is all very true, but not to your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, unleſs you had prov'd alſo, what you do but inſinuate, <hi>That we have ſeparated our ſelves from the Doctrine and Government of the Church of Chriſt.</hi> Which Words I wonder that you were not afraid to uſe, when they lay ſo fair to be turn'd upon your ſelves. For we are no leſs ſure, that many of your Doctrines are no parts of the Doctrine of <hi>that</hi> Church; and that <hi>Rome</hi>'s being the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Miſtreſs of all Churches, was not the Government of <hi>that</hi> Church over which the Apoſtles were, <hi>&amp;c. Overſeers</hi> for their time, than we are, that ſuch a Church was eſtabliſhed in the World. And therefore, if they who ſeparate themſelves from the <hi>Doctrine and Government of the Church of Chriſt,</hi> as it was firſt eſtabliſh'd, cannot hope for Salvation: Pray look to your ſelves as to that Point, inſtead of contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that you are the <hi>only Catholick</hi> Church, out of which there is no hope of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>As to what you would inſinuate, that there muſt be in the Church a Succeſſion of Paſtors to the Worlds end, who ſhould no
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40809:69"/> more err in teaching, than the Apoſtles themſelves did, and that your Church has that Succeſſion. I muſt tell you as to the firſt, that it is by no means proved from <hi>John</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 16. ſince what is there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to the Apoſtles, is not promis'd to the Church of all Ages, ſo as it was to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. The Spirit of God abode with the Apoſtles for ever, that is, ſo long as they liv'd, to guide them into the knowledge of Truth, and by them to guide the Church in all After-Ages. There are many things in this Diſcourſe of our Saviour to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which cannot be applied to any Age of the Church after theirs. And therefore what is, and what is not limited to them, muſt be argued out from the Nature of the things themſelves which are ſaid. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though you will not have this Promiſe limited to the Perſons of the Apoſtles, but annext to their Function, as in ſome ſence I grant it may be; yet you ought to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice, that the Promiſe is however limited by a Condition, even in the Words foregoing and following the Promiſe: <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments,</hi> and there the Condition is once expreſs'd. For it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth.</hi> And now mark once again what follows,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40809:70"/> 
                     <hi>Whom the World cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him.</hi> Where, if by the <hi>World</hi> be meant worldly and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, as I believe you will grant; you ſee here is no abſolute Promiſe of ſuch a Guidance to a Succeſſion of Paſtors, as ſhall make it at any time of the Church <hi>Hereſie</hi> to contradict whatſoever they teach, or <hi>Schiſm</hi> to withdraw from their Obedience. As to the laſt; If you had prov'd ſuch a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Infallible Teachers as you ſpeak of; yet I tell you once more, that the hardeſt part of your Task would be ſtill behind; which is to prove, That you have had all along, and ſtill have that Succeſſion; which I deſire you to do in your next, if you can, if it be but for the Inſtruction of a <hi>Lay-man</hi> that deſires to be led into all Truth, neceſſary, or even profitable for his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And becauſe I would not have you loſe your labour, I will open my greateſt Difficulty againſt this Belief. I am ſure you cannot go about this Work without taking Scripture in to furniſh out your Argument. Now I deſire you to bring me ſuch Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which ſhall at leaſt make it as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that your Church was always to have a Succeſſion of Infallible Teachers, as it is to me from divers other Scriptures evident, that your Paſtors have moſt certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted the Doctrine of the Scriptures.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40809:70"/> And when you have done this, you ſhall hear farther from me. In the mean time, your looſe Affirmations concerning the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church have been ſo often anſwered, that you need not wonder that a Lay-man of our Church can tell what to ſay to them.</p>
                  <p>But to come to that wherein I am parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly concern'd. You are diſturb'd at my ſaying, <hi>That the Worſhip, Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>are ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dangerous; that nothing but Invincible Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, of which God only can judge, can give us any reaſonable hopes of their Salvation who live and die in their Communion.</hi> Now ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the uncharitableneſs of this does not lie in ſuppoſing that <hi>Invincible Ignorance</hi> will be pleadable in this Caſe, for 'tis a Plea which will go a great way amongſt thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion; which, I ſay, with the more Confidence, becauſe in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Countries where I have been, the People ſeem to me to have the faireſt Claim to the benefit of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that can be well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>Now ſince at laſt you are brought in this Pamphlet of yours to agree with Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that <hi>Ignorance</hi> will ſave Men, and that we yield the greateſt part of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40809:71"/> have an indiſputable Right to it; are not the <hi>Protestants</hi> charitable to a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? If this will not pleaſe you, I do not know what will. Surely, Sir, you do not expect that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould believe and ſay, that you, with all your Errors about you, are in as ſafe a way to Salvation, as they themſelves who have renounced them? If this could be, what, I pray ye, made our Fore-fathers ſuffer themſelves to be ſeparated from your Communion? or make us that we cannot joyn with you? Certainly this was, and is ſtill nothing but want of ſound Faith, purity of Doctrines and Worſhip. And I know nothing elſe can, or ever was pretended to juſtifie our Separation. And this alone one would think might be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to vindicate my Aſſertion from being <hi>uncharitable.</hi> But perhaps I may do it more by and by.</p>
                  <p>But you'll tell me, that nevertheleſs <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> are <hi>as</hi> uncharitable as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and come not <hi>an Ace</hi> behind them. Indeed I ſhould be very ſorry this were true. And though it is, I know, an untoward Queſtion <hi>to Papiſts,</hi> yet I muſt ask, How do you prove this, Sir? Why thus. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allow Salvation to <hi>Papiſts</hi> upon Invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Ignorance, and <hi>Papiſts</hi> do the ſame to <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> I muſt confeſs that in this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40809:71"/> Paper of yours, you grant Salvation to <hi>Proteſtants who live piouſly, and repent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cererely of all Offences, and through invincible Ignorance remain in that Communion.</hi> Now whatever Truth there is in the Saying it ſelf, yet from you we look upon this Conceſſion as a piece of <hi>New</hi> Popery. The <hi>Old</hi> Popery was, <hi>Proteſtancy unrepented of Damns.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Invincible Ignorance,</hi> nor <hi>Piety,</hi> nor any <hi>Repentance</hi> that included not a leaving the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Communion, and joining with the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> could Save. But here we take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that of this, as well as of all the other unreaſonable Pieces of <hi>Old</hi> Popery, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at laſt to be aſham'd, or at leaſt to think it for the Intereſt of your Deſign on foot, to <hi>deny</hi> them, or diſguiſe and ſoften them, that ſo they may go the better down with thoſe People who are not ſo well read in your Controverſies, and ſuſpect no Snake in the Graſs. But to go on with my Point. Did not the Author of <hi>Charity Miſtaken,</hi> and <hi>Charity maintain'd</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Charity maintain'd, <hi>p. 1. c. 7. Sect. 6.</hi> and in divers other places of that, and Charity Miſtaken.</note> (which produc'd that <hi>incomparable</hi> Book of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>) ſtiffly and boldly aſſert, <hi>That all Roman Catholicks, not one excepted</hi> — Do with unanimous Conſent believe and profeſs that Proteſtancy unrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted deſtroys Salvation? Did not the Jeſuite, in his Relation of Biſhop <hi>Land</hi>'s Conference,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40809:72"/> ſwear upon his <hi>Soul, That there was but one ſaving Faith, and that is the Roman?</hi> And now in our days, has not a<note n="*" place="margin">Lucilla <hi>and</hi> Elizabeth.</note> late Paper endeavour'd to make us as great <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> as the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts?</hi> And according to you, can <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> dying ſuch, go to Heaven? And does not that Author force St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to tell us in plain Terms, <hi>That whoſoever is ſeparated from the Catholick Church,</hi> (by which, againſt all Modeſty and Truth, you always mean your own <hi>particular</hi> Church) <hi>how laudably ſoever he thinks himſelf to live, for this only Crime,</hi> that he is disjoyn'd from the Unity of Chriſt, (that is to ſay, in your Language, the Pope) <hi>he ſhall not have Life, but the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Pray, Sir, be ſo kind, if not to me, yet to your ſelf, to reconcile theſe Sayings with what you ſay, viz. <hi>That there is no Papiſts but what will grant ſuch Proteſtants hopes of Salvation, who living piouſly, and repenting ſincerely of all Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and through invincible Ignorance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in that Communion.</hi> Where's the Truth and Honeſty now of your Aſſertion, That there is <hi>No Papiſt, &amp;c.?</hi> When I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy produced three, and perhaps if I pleas'd, could name three hundred. What do you call this amongſt you? We call it contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting one another. Well, however pray obſerve, here's two ſorts of Popery. But
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40809:72"/> which muſt a Man rely on for Orthodox? The <hi>Old</hi> or the <hi>New</hi> Popery. I muſt confeſs I am inclin'd to believe the <hi>New</hi> to be the beſt, but certainly the <hi>Old</hi> Popery is the true ſtanding Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But ſuppoſe we ſtood in need of the <hi>New,</hi> what ſhould we be the better for't, unleſs the Conceſſion were ſtampt with the <hi>Fiſhers</hi> Seal? For you that deal it out to the World are but a private obſcure Man, and your Church is no more bound to ſtand to what you ſay, than mine is to what I ſay, unleſs it be Truth. This that you grant, at beſt, is but a ſign that you have a better Opinion of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion than the generality of your Writers. But to let this paſs. I will now prove this Truth beyond any poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Papiſts</hi> deny Salvation to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> remaining <hi>ſuch,</hi> and that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> grant a <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of it to <hi>Papiſts</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining <hi>ſuch:</hi> And therefore by conſequence, the <hi>first</hi> muſt needs be on the <hi>uncharitable,</hi> and the <hi>laſt</hi> on the <hi>charitable</hi> ſide. And this I ſhall do by ſhewing, that <hi>our</hi> Charity is ſo great to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> want of it ſo apparent to us, that they have abus'd it into an Argument againſt us. And this is ſo notoriouſly true, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not aſham'd to boaſt of it in their Writings and Converſation; thinking thereby to draw weak Perſons, that cannot conſider where the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40809:73"/> Cheat of the Argument lies to be of their Church: And with this deceitful Argument, which they have fram'd from <hi>our Exceſs</hi> of Charity to them, and <hi>their want</hi> of it to us, I have heard them make a great noiſe, and tell of the mighty Feats it has done. But certainly it was amongſt ſuch as had thrown away all their <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe;</hi> or elſe if there had been no other thing to recommend the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they would have thought that to be the beſt and ſafeſt Church, which eminently has the very Beauty and Form of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>viz. Charity,</hi> which the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo conſtantly and largely maintains and practiſes. But the Argument is this, — <hi>You Proteſtants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Salvation may be had in the Romiſh Church, but we Papiſts utterly deny it to yours; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Confeſſion of both ſides, thoſe that are in our Church are ſafe; but there is great queſtion concerning Proteſtants, remaining ſuch, for none but themſelves ſay they can be ſaved.</hi> What think you now, Sir, of the <hi>Proteſtants Charity,</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts want of it?</hi> Is here any Proviſion made for poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by <hi>Invincible Ignorance?</hi> If this does not prove that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have <hi>ſome</hi> Charity for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>they none</hi> at all for us <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> I do not know what can. And that you could be ignorant of theſe things, and this Argument ſo commonly us'd by your Men, when they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40809:73"/> would deceive the well-meaning People of our Church, you muſt excuſe me if I cannot believe it. With what Face then, Sir, could you tell the <hi>gaping Multitude,</hi> as you think fit to call the poor honeſt People, <hi>That Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do not advance the Damnation of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants one Ace farther againſt them, than the Proteſtants againſt Papiſts; and that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Proteſtants in this affair is the ſame in reference to each other; and the Proteſtants are as uncharitable Damners of the Papiſts, as they are made to be of the Proteſtants?</hi> And now the matter being brought to this Iſſue, pray, Sir, tell me who are the <hi>unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Damners, Thunderers of Hell and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation! Who impoſes upon the People? who are the injurious Slanderers? And who is it that render the Papiſts black and odious for their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs,</hi> but the Papiſts themſelves? Certainly, Sir, if <hi>your Eye-ſight had not been horribly indiſpos'd with the malignant Influence of Rome,</hi> you would have ſeen, that the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Damners</hi> are the <hi>Papiſts</hi> only. For ſhame learn, tho' late, to maintain your Cauſe by <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> or let it periſh.</p>
                  <p>But I foreſee that you may take it a little ill, that our Charity extends not to the <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Judicious,</hi> in the number of which I dare ſay you reckon your ſelf. Now for theſe Perſons who are to conſider, whether
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40809:74"/> they know or believe ſuch and ſuch things to be falſe, which yet for <hi>Worldly</hi> Ends they maintain for Truths; or after an honeſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch, cannot by any means diſcover them to be Errors, hindred by Prepoſſeſſion, Education, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For theſe laſt Perſons I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee why <hi>Invincible Ignorance</hi> will not comprehend them as well as the ordinary and unlearned People: For I cannot tell what Invincible Ignorance is, unleſs it be this, <hi>That after all our beſt Endeavours according to our utmoſt Ability and Means, we yet cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern which is Error, and which is Truth.</hi> But now for the firſt ſort, who maintain known <hi>Errors</hi> for <hi>Truths,</hi> againſt their Conſcience, only for <hi>Secular</hi> Advantages (in the number of which I pray God you be not) what would you have us believe or ſay of them? <hi>God Almighty</hi> Himſelf has made no Proviſion, that we know of, for bold, wilful and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners. We <hi>judge no Man that hath a Maſter to ſtand and fall to. Charity hopeth all things.</hi> And I muſt tell you my Mind freely, for I have vow'd to follow <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> where-ever they lead me: That I think it had been better, and more like Chriſtians, if no Member of either Church had medled with the Events of things, and leap'd into God's Judgmens-ſeat, and pronounc'd final Sentence upon Souls. That certainly being a Secret and Prerogative
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40809:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> peculiar to <hi>God,</hi> who only is <hi>the Searcher of Mens Hearts,</hi> knows all things, and has an abſolute Dominion over his Creatures, and can do all that his Juſtice, his Goodneſs, and his Mercy <hi>wills.</hi> Had the Paſtors of each Church done no more, but barely and plainly done the Truths of <hi>God,</hi> or what they ſincerely believ'd to be ſo, and left the Judgment of Perſons to him, that always <hi>judgeth right,</hi> they had doubtleſs done their Duty. But 'tis evident the Men of your Church <hi>firſt</hi> us'd it to work upon Mens Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and what they could not perſwade their Underſtandings to for want of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they were reſolv'd to do it by fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. For 'tis too apparent, that more are ſway'd by Fear than Love; more are drawn by their Affections and Paſſions, than by their Reaſon; and ſome of our Church-men to countermine your Policy, found it expedient to imitate you, as far as Truth and Chriſtian Charity would permit them. And this may ſuffice alſo to apologize for my uſing it in my <hi>Preface,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It now remains, Sir, that I ſpeak to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing which ſeem'd to diſturb you; which is, Whether I am a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> or a <hi>Clergy-man.</hi> For I find you wavering about it; and therefore I'll endeavour to fix you, tho' in a doubtful caſe; Why ſhould not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40809:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> Charity have inclin'd you that brag of ſo much, to believe me when I profeſs my ſelf a <hi>Lay-man?</hi> Well, but <hi>I ſpeak ſo like a Clergy-man, ſo almoſt in the very Words and Phraſes of a Doctor of my Church, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctor mention'd</hi> in your <hi>Laſt Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly, that you cannot but take what I ſay for Church-ſence, dropping through a Lay-Pen.</hi> Sir, I muſt needs thank you for the Honour you do me, in <hi>taking</hi> me to ſpeak like ſuch great Men; but I have not Vanity enough to believe that I do. Yet thus much I'll confeſs, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to live no longer than I can, if not ſpeak, yet love and admire the Church of <hi>England-Sence.</hi> But is it impoſſible for a <hi>Lay-man</hi> to ſpeak like a <hi>Clergy-man?</hi> Does Holy Orders make ſuch a difference? Or do you imagine I have never read any of our Churches Writers? Why may not then my Mind be tinctured by them? And ſo what I ſpeak or write, bear ſome reſemblance to them? Is there not many a Son like his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And how do you know but I am the Son of a Clergy-man? and ſo by Blood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive ſomething of their way of Writing. But to make an end; I fancy, Sir, that you, or whoever was the Author of the <hi>Firſt Part of the Papiſt Miſrepreſented, &amp;c.</hi> and ſome others of your Church, have found to your Grief and Shame, that either of theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors you ſpeak of, could, if they had pleas'd
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40809:75"/> to have undertaken ſo mean a Work, have writ another ſort of a <hi>Preface</hi> than I have done, to the diſadvantage of the <hi>French</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery now imitated in <hi>England.</hi> Let the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Performance prevail over you, to believe that neither of them made it. But indeed you are <hi>injurious</hi> to them to fancy they would be guilty of ſuch indirect deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. No, no, Sir, the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have a better Cauſe, they need uſe no Arts, or Tricks, no feign'd Miracles, no bold Untruths, no malicious Whiſpers and Slanders to ſupport and defend it, nor put Shams upon the World. This Practice is none of theirs; and if you pleaſe that may be added, as a Mark to prove ours a <hi>True</hi> Church: And indeed I could eaſily perſwade my ſelf to believe, that your own Practice, and that of your Party, was in your Thoughts, when this Fancy entred into your Brain. But in a word, and to put you out of pain about theſe two Doctors, (for I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not blame you for dreading them) I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that neither of them made that <hi>Preface;</hi> and once more, that I who now write this Letter am a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> and writ that <hi>Preface,</hi> ſuch as 'tis. And if I could but be <hi>infallibly</hi> certain, that the <hi>old</hi> Popery was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in the point of Malice, Revenge, and ſeeking occaſion againſt thoſe who never ſo little oppoſe or hinder the Deſigns of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:40809:76"/> I would give you entire ſatisfaction in this Particular, and not only tell you my Name, but where I live. But becauſe I cannot get out of my Thoughts ſome late Actions, and that hard Uſage of the brave Author of <hi>Wholſom Advices,</hi> &amp;c. I fear leſt <hi>Old</hi> Popery may be practic'd upon me too; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think it but common Prudence to conceal my ſelf: For, to tell you true, I am not yet weary of that little Happineſs I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
                  <p>But, Sir, you make <hi>your</hi> Miſrepreſenter tell the World, that I am <hi>dabling out of my Element;</hi> by which one would think, that after all you believ'd I am a Lay-man. Well, but how out of my Element? May not a Lay-man tell Truth, and do good to his Neighbour's Soul? Is God's Spirit, is all Knowledge limitted to Holy Orders? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are ſome Functions appropriated to <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> ſuch as Adminiſtring the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> does it therefore follow, that a Lay-man may neither write nor diſcourſe of any Matters of Religion? Pray, Sir, does that Command, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf,</hi> oblige <hi>Lay-men</hi> as well as <hi>Clergy-men?</hi> If it does, and ſince I may edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelf, why, I beſeech you, not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And can a Man expreſs his Charity to his Neighbour in a higher manner than in
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40809:76"/> Spiritual Things? But the Arguments are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite which might be us'd in this Caſe. And therefore I ſhall only ask you whether <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> and many other of the Ancient Fathers, writ not about Religion when they were Lay-men? Nay, more; did not Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> and Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>Laymen</hi> into Councils? And pray, what was <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> but an Earl, and meer Lay-man? and Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England?</hi> But above all, what was that Prince who wrote againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> for which the Pope thought fit to beſtow the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi> upon him? But indeed why ſhould it ſeem ſtrange, that you and your Church ſhould find fault with Lay-men's medling in Controverſies of Religion, eſpecially againſt you, when you dare totally bar Lay-mens <hi>reading</hi> the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> for which they have a Command from God, <hi>Search the Scriptures;</hi> and perſwade them to put out their Eyes, and throw away their Reaſon, which <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> has given them to be their Guide through this deceitful World. And yet I dare ſay, that if a <hi>Lay-man</hi> would undertake ſo <hi>knotty</hi> a piece of Work, as to write in Defence of your Church, that you would not tell him that he was <hi>dab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of his Element,</hi> tho' he were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a <hi>Profligate Poet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:40809:77"/>
                  <p>I paſs over your unhandſom Language, and 'tis below me to return it. But I cannot but ſtand amaz'd, to find a Member of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a Maintainer of the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> make <hi>his</hi> Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenter ſay, That the Proteſtant Teachers <hi>know the People they have to deal with—That their diſcerning Faculties are ſtupify'd — That they'll paſs over fifty Contradictions, without once ſtumbling; and that there's no fear of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, How can this be?</hi> No, Sir, the Teachers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not guilty of this Tyranny. We are Members of a Church that invites all her Children to the higheſt Attainment of Knowledge, and teaches them, that a <hi>reaſonable Service</hi> is the moſt acceptable to God; and impoſes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon them, that either deſtroys or contradicts their Reaſon and Senſes; that not only allows her Children to read the Holy Scriptures, but beſeeches them to do it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they do it with a modeſt Dependence on their <hi>lawful</hi> Teachers, for the ſence of <hi>ſome</hi> Texts, which may not be ſo clear to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are unacquainted with the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Languages in which the Holy Scriptures were writ, and the Cuſtoms and Manners of the People and Countries where they were penn'd. In a Word, the Church of <hi>England</hi> allows a private Liberty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining all things ſhe propounds, and does
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40809:77"/> not expect that Men ſhould follow her blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. She requires indeed Obedience in thoſe <hi>few</hi> Points which are <hi>abſolutely</hi> neceſſary to Salvation, becauſe they are ſo plain, that it is impoſſible for an honeſt and ſound Mind to queſtion them: But for things of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Nature, ſhe only deſires that for the ſake of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Order</hi> and <hi>Decency,</hi> that her Children would not diſpute about them. In fine, ſhe is very ſure, that <hi>they,</hi> and they <hi>only,</hi> are her <hi>true</hi> Children, her moſt <hi>ſincere</hi> Members, who are the moſt obedient to <hi>Scripture,</hi> and moſt ready to yield to the Evidence of <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus, Sir, I have endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Peace to your Mind, by ſhewing that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not at all uncharitable, but that Papiſts are; and that I am a Lay-man, and yet may meddle in Divinity, and not be <hi>dabling out of my Element.</hi> And now I hope you'l be no longer in a Fright of thoſe two Doctors you hinted; for, aſſure your ſelf, that unleſs there be occaſion to defend a poor <hi>Lay-man</hi> of their Church, as far as the Truth and the Religion of it are concern'd (for you may poſſibly hear from me upon ſome other Point) theſe two Doctors are better employ'd, than to trouble themſelves with you.</p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40809:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>But if againſt this plain Proof, that the Papiſts are the <hi>only</hi> uncharitable Perſons, you will yet rub your Forehead, and make <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> as bad, what Remedy? Truth will be Truth ſtill. And however it fares with us, we have over and above this Satisfaction; and you know the Teſtimony of an Enemy proves much, that <hi>to give us our due,</hi> you ſay, we <hi>are the moſt Gentile and courtly Damners</hi> that can poſſibly be met with. Now for the Reward of this frank Acknowledgment, I wiſh with all my Soul, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> could ſay ſo much of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> But the continual ſound of <hi>Peſtilent Hereticks, Damn'd Schiſmaticks,</hi> and ſuch rude and unchriſtian Names every where heard, will not poſſibly permit them.</p>
                  <p>To conclude all; I ſhall only deſire you, for prevention of more Trouble than needs be, (and I have known a great Controverſie to ariſe from a matter leſs liable to a Miſtake) to take notice, that the very Point in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, is not. Whether the Religion of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts</hi> is the Trueſt or Safeſt? For he that believes the Second Commandment was given by God, and that it is not lawful to worſhip any <hi>Being</hi> but only <hi>God,</hi> who gave <hi>being</hi> to all Things, need not be to ſeek in that: Neither is it, whether the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts</hi> are the <hi>moſt</hi> uncharitable? But, in Truth, the preſent Queſtion is, Whether the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40809:78"/> 
                     <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not the <hi>only</hi> uncharitable Perſons? And I think I have fully prov'd that they are ſo, even from the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves.</p>
                  <p>Sir, I heartily wiſh you and your Party would, before it would be too late, ſhew ſo much Charity to your ſelves and others, to leave off deceiving the poor Souls, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing the Peace of Mankind, tho' by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in your Enterprize, you might ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to the higheſt Temporal Felicities, and by deſiſting, ſuffer the greateſt of Humane Miſeries.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And I am Your very humble Servant.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:40809:79"/>
                  <head>A <hi>POSTSCRIPT</hi> by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the <hi>Repreſenter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HAving leave to fill up this place, I uſe it to rectifie an Error in the 119th Page of the laſt Anſwer to the <hi>Repreſenter;</hi> where an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Cochleus</hi> was omitted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Correction, and ſo he is brought in for the Reporter of thoſe Famous Fictions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Luther</hi>'s Death; whereas his part in it is the leaſt, the reſt being reported by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, particularly by <hi>Pontacus, Lindan,</hi> and our Country-man <hi>W. Reinolds. Cochleus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with the Epiſtle concerning <hi>Luther</hi>'s lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End, publiſhed by him <hi>fol.</hi> 298. of his Hiſtory, tells the manner of his Death o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. But <hi>Thyraeus</hi> a Jeſuit was the Man whom I had in my Mind, for contradicting thoſe with whom he agreed in the general Deſign of Defamation. For he ſays, <hi>That day when</hi> Luther <hi>died, thoſe poſſeſſed Perſons in a Town of</hi> Brabant <hi>(where there were very many) who expected deliverance by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of St.</hi> Dymna <hi>(of which for many
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40809:79"/> years many had experience) were delivered from the Devils, and a little after were again poſſeſſed. For the Caſe was this; that the cruel Spirits again tormenting thoſe miſerable perſons, being asked, where they had beſtowed themſelves the day before, anſwered, That by the Command of their Chief they were called forth to the Funeral of the New Prophet, and their faithful Fellow-worker,</hi> Luther, <hi>and had been preſent at it. Which matter was confirmed by a Servant of</hi> Luther, <hi>who was with him while he was dying miſerably: For as he was looking out of the Caſement for freſh Air, he was greatly affrighted to ſee more than once I know not how many black ugly Spirits skipping and dancing not far off. And this alſo was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Crows, which with a fearful noiſe accompanied the Body of</hi> Luther <hi>as it was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to</hi> Wittemberg. Which wiſe Tale (<hi>De Demoniacis par.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 99.) is alſo abetted by <hi>Flor. Raemundus de Orig. Haereſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 40. but does by no means agree with what <hi>Reinolds</hi> reports in his <hi>Calvino-Turciſmus, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 957. that <hi>Luther,</hi> after a merry Supper, was in the Night ſuddainly ſtrangled by his Wife. This Buſineſs, as they have ſeverally reported it, is a very notable Inſtance how early they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Trade of <hi>Miſrepreſenting matters of Fact.</hi> But more of this when there is more occaſion.</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:40809:80"/>
                  <p>I ſhall only add, that the Authority I have for ſaying that they ſpread ſuch like lewd Stories of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Death before he was dead, is indeed the Authority of Proteſtant Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and chiefly of <hi>Phil. Lonicerus</hi> in his <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrum Hiſtoricum;</hi> nor could it be expected that we ſhould have any other.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:80"/>
                  <head>Some Books lately Printed for <hi>J Robinſon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>BIſhop <hi>Hopkin</hi>'s Practical Expoſition on the Ten Commandments.</item>
                     <item>—Six Sermons on <hi>Acts</hi> 26.28.</item>
                     <item>Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s Vol. of Sermons on ſeveral Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</item>
                     <item>Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> Enquiry into ſeveral difficult Texts of Scripture.</item>
                     <item>—His Diſcourſe on the Authority, Style and Perfection of the Holy Scriptures.</item>
                     <item>Directions for our more Devout Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the time of Divine Service, with a ſhort <hi>Rationale</hi> on the Common Prayer.</item>
                     <item>The Curate's Advice to his Pariſhioners for the keeping Holy the Lord's Day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The New State of <hi>England</hi> under Their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> in Three Parts. The Second Edition, with great Improvements, <hi>viz.</hi> A Geographical and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical Account of the Principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> a Conciſe Hiſtory of the late Revolution, a Liſt of the Baronets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:81"/>
                  <head>Books Printed for <hi>Tho. Newborough</hi> at the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>A Critical Hiſtory of the Text of the New Teſtament, wherein is firmly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd the Truth of thoſe Acts on which the Foundation of Chriſtian Religion is laid. By <hi>Rich. Simon,</hi> Prieſt. 4to.</item>
                     <item>A Critical Hiſtory of the Verſion of the New Teſtament. By <hi>Richard Simon:</hi> With a Refutation of ſuch Paſſages as ſeem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> 1692.</item>
                     <item>The New-years-gift Compleat, in Six Parts: Compoſed of Prayers and Meditations for every Day in the Week; with Devotions for the Sacrament, Lent, and other Occaſions. 12o.</item>
                     <item>A Sermon Preach'd before the Queen at <hi>Whitehall, Feb.</hi> 12. 1691. By <hi>William Fleetwood,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</item>
                     <item>A Sermon Preach'd before the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Lord Mayor and Court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, at St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> the 11th of <hi>April,</hi> 1692. being the Faſt-Day. By <hi>W. Fleetwood,</hi> Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40809:81"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
